<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Heaven and hell, or, The unchangeable state of happiness or misery for all mankind in another world occasion'd by the repentance and death of Mr. Shetterden Thomas, who departed this life April 7, 1700, aetat. 26 : preach'd and publish'd at the desire and direction of the deceased ... / by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34242</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14153769</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14153769</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102130</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102130)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Heaven and hell, or, The unchangeable state of happiness or misery for all mankind in another world occasion'd by the repentance and death of Mr. Shetterden Thomas, who departed this life April 7, 1700, aetat. 26 : preach'd and publish'd at the desire and direction of the deceased ... / by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 186 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Heptinstall for John Sprint ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XVI, 26 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Eschatology.</term>
               <term>Future life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102130:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Heaven and Hell;</hi> OR, The Unchangeable State OF Happineſs or Miſery For all MANKIND In Another WORLD.</p>
            <p>Occaſion'd by the <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of Mr. <hi>Shetterden Thomas,</hi> who departed this Life, <hi>April</hi> 7, 1700. <hi>Aetat.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>Preach'd and Publiſh'd at the Deſire and Direction of the Deceaſed. With ſome Particulars he order'd ſhould be mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in hope of doing Good to Others.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Shower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a further Account of ſome Paſſages of his laſt Sickneſs, by a Pious Lady, who often viſited him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Heptinſtall</hi> for <hi>John Sprint,</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102130:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102130:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory TO Mr. DANIEL THOMAS OF HIGHGATE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Should look on my ſelf as juſtly expos'd to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the World, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Treatiſe of ſo ſerious a Nature, and ſuch Important Conſequence, I ſhould prefix any thing that looks like <hi>Flattery,</hi> either of <hi>You,</hi> or of the <hi>Honoured Lady,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:102130:3"/>Relation of whoſe Diſcourſe with Your Deceaſed Brother, in his laſt Sickneſs, is here an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd. How much You rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon'd Your ſelf indebted to Her for that Inſtance of her Friendſhip, I have heard You acknowledge with great Thankfulneſs.</p>
            <p>You have reaſon to own the ſingular Goodneſs of God, who gave him ſo Merciful a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Repentance, and his Grace, (as we charitably hope,) to make uſe of it to better purpoſe than moſt late Penitents do. I endeavour'd to be Faithful to him while he liv'd; and to fulfil his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire after his Deceaſe, in what
<pb facs="tcp:102130:3"/>was Preach'd, and is now more largely Publiſh'd. May neither You, nor I, loſe the Impreſſions of this Inſtructive Providence, or of that Awful Subject, it led me to treat of! If no Others ſhould profit by either, I wiſh with all my Heart, and moſt earneſtly beg it of God, that You and Yours may.</p>
            <p>Sir, I ſhall only put You in mind with what Kindneſs and Affection he ſent for Your Children a little before his Death, and recommended to You, and my Siſter, a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Care of their Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Knowledge and Fear of God; and mention'd it
<pb facs="tcp:102130:4"/>with Pleaſure, that they were like to have that Advantage. May both of them live to have it, and improve it! to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God in the World, and partake of the Bleſſings of the Everlaſting Covenant! <hi>And may All mine do ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe!</hi> Which is the Earneſt Prayer of him, who is with unfeigned Reſpect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Affectionate Brother, and Faithful Servant, J. Shower.</signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>May <hi>ult. 1700.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:102130:4"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>INtroduction. <hi>The Scope of the Parable. The Different Conditions of Mankind after Death,</hi> p. 4. <hi>The Souls of Good Men are in a State of Reſt and Happineſs, before the Reſurrection. Why called</hi> Abraham's Boſom, p. 7. <hi>A poſitive State of Miſery and Torment for the Wicked, in another World,</hi> p. 13-28. <hi>Both States af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable.</hi> p. 29. <hi>The Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Saints Everlaſting,</hi> p. 31. <hi>The Gulf fix'd as to the Miſery of the Wicked, without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe or End,</hi> p. 36. <hi>The</hi> Socinian <hi>Doctrine, concerning the</hi> Annihilation <hi>of the Wicked after the Day of Judgment, diſprov'd from Scripture. The Objections againſt the Endleſs Miſery of the Wicked, anſwer'd,</hi> p. 47.</p>
            <p>Application. Inference 1. <hi>Now or Never is the Seaſon to prepare for Eternity,</hi> p. 55. (2.) <hi>How valuable a Talent is the Time of our preſent Life?</hi> p. 58. <hi>The Evil of Idleneſs.</hi> (3.) <hi>How Awful, and of how great Conſequence for any one to die, and paſs into the other World?</hi> p. 63. <hi>What a Change will Death make to a Wicked Man?</hi> (4.) <hi>We may take our Meaſures of Men's Wiſdom or Folly, according to their Care or Negligence in preparing for the Eternal World,</hi> p. 77. <hi>How Inconſiderable is the longeſt Life on Earth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd with an Endleſs Duration?</hi> A thouſand Years in God's Sight but as one Day, <hi>p.</hi> 86. (Laſtly,) <hi>What a hazard to delay Repentance to the laſt Hour, or to a Sick-Bed?</hi> p. 86. <hi>The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb facs="tcp:102130:5"/>of the</hi> Thief on the Croſs <hi>conſidered as Extraordinary, and prov'd to give no Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſuch a Delay,</hi> p. 88. <hi>The Excellency of his ſhort Prayer,</hi> Lord, Remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom! <hi>p.</hi> 95. <hi>Death-Bed Repentance deceitfull, and uncomfortable,</hi> p. 103.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exhortation</hi> (1.) <hi>To be Eſtabliſht in the Belief of the Scripture Doctrine, concerning the two Eternal States; and labour to be ſuitably affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Conſideration of</hi> Heaven <hi>and</hi> Hell, <hi>p.</hi> 106. (2.) <hi>Let us hearken to</hi> Moſes <hi>and the</hi> Prophets, <hi>to</hi> Chriſt <hi>and his</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>if we would ever have a Place in</hi> Abraham's Boſom, <hi>and eſcape the Torments of Hell,</hi> p. 121. <hi>They who will not believe Scripture Revelation, 'tis probable would not be perſwaded though one came from the Dead,</hi> p. 123.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Account of the laſt Sickneſs, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of Mr.</hi> Sh. T. <hi>p.</hi> 132. <hi>Some Particulars warn'd againſt, by his Deſire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A further Account of ſome Paſſages of his laſt Sickneſs, by a Pious Lady who often viſited him.</hi> p. 156.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102130:5"/>
            <head>HEAVEN and HELL; OR, The Unchangeable State of <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,</hi> or <hi>Miſery, after</hi> Death.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>S. LUKE XVI. 26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And beſides all this, between us and you, there is a great Gulf fixed:—</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE are told by the Wiſe Man what becomes of the Body and the Soul when they part at Death; how the Body that was fram'd out of the Duſt of the Ground, returns thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and the Soul which is of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Original returns to GOD, the Father of Spirits, (to <hi>Elohim,</hi> which ſignifies a Judge as well as a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,) to be diſpos'd of by him in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102130:6"/>another World.
<note place="margin">Eccl. xii. 3</note> 
               <hi>Then ſhall the Duſt return to its Earth, and the Spirit to God that gave it.</hi> It is not to be annihilated, extinguiſhed, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd, but returns to GOD as the final Arbiter of its Eternal State. That there is ſuch a State of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs or Miſery, of Reſt or Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for departed Souls; and that both ſtates are unchangable, is what this Parable may inſtruct us in. There is <hi>a Gulf fix'd</hi> between the Bleſſed and Miſerable after Death, either ſort unalterably Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, or unchangeably Miſerable. There is an irreverſible Decree of Heaven to determine the Felicity of the Saints to be everlaſting, and to conclude the Wicked in a ſtate of Miſery without Relief, or End. As there is no fear of Change for the Happy Souls in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, ſo is there no hope of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viation or Period of the wretched condition of Sinners in Hell. This is the Important Subject I would now Explain, Evidence, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102130:6"/>And can there be any that more deſerves and calls for your moſt ſerious Attention.</p>
            <p>It is one part of the Deſign, and Scope of this Parable of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, concerning the <hi>Rich-man</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> to affirm this. A <hi>Parable</hi> it muſt be granted, tho' mixt with ſomewhat Hiſtorical, as the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Poor-man by name, who may be ſuppos'd to have been no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious and known among the <hi>Jews,</hi> for his extream Poverty and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs: The different State and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Men departed this Life is expreſs'd by our Saviour in a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical way, the more effectually to inſinuate the Truths he would teach us with the greater Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to move the Affections of his Hearers.</p>
            <p>From this Parabolical Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the different Condition of the Souls of Men after Death, I would obſerve, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the ſtate of Mankind after Death, is a Condition of Real, Poſitive Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102130:7"/>or Miſery, of Comfort, or Torment. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That both theſe States are fixed and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. The Bleſſed ſhall never be Miſerable, and the Miſerable ſhall never ceaſe to be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> When the Union between the Soul and Body is diſſolved by Death, the Soul of every Man paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth into a ſtate of Happineſs or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. This we may plainly learn from this Parable, <hi>Ver.</hi> 22, 23. <hi>When the Beggar died, he was carry'd into Abraham's Boſom: And the Rich Man alſo died, and was buried,</hi> (it may be he had a pompous Funeral, the only Advantage, if it be one, of the Rich above the Poor, after they are dead) <hi>and in Hell he lift up his Eyes, being in torment.</hi>—The one had his good things here, the other his evil things: But now the <hi>one is comforted,</hi> the <hi>other torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Ver. 25.</p>
            <p>This is an account of departed Souls before the <hi>Reſurrection:</hi> for the Rich Man is ſaid to be in Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102130:7"/>while his five Brethren were alive; and he deſired that One ſhould be ſent to admoniſh and warn them, that they might not come to this place of Torment. We read but of two ſorts at the Day of Judgment, <hi>The Sheep</hi> and <hi>the Goats;</hi> the one pronounced Bleſſed, the other Accurſed. The one to <hi>go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into everlaſting Life, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into everlaſting Puniſhment.</hi> God hath told us, that <hi>he will render to every Man according to his Works.</hi> And as Man is capable by his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Nature, of giving an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Actions, and of being rewarded or puniſh'd in another World; thoſe very Faculties which give him this Capacity, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh him from the inferiour Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, do ſuggeſt this; and fill him with Hopes and Fears accordingly. So that comparing the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Juſtice, and the other Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Perfections of God, with the preſent Diſpenſations of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſome ſuch different ſtate, by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102130:8"/>the very Light of Nature, as well as Scripture, may be expected hereafter.</p>
            <p>The aſſurance therefore of God's being infinitely Wiſe and Juſt, gives us to expect that a Difference will be made between theſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, which we ſee is not done now. And the rather becauſe Civil Society can never be ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if there be no Reſtraint upon the Luſts and Paſſions of Men; and theſe can never be ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd, without the Hopes and Fears of another World; and as theſe therefore are natural, we may conclude 'em true, and that there is another World, and a Future State of Happineſs or Miſery. We read in this Parable, of the different Character and Condition of the <hi>Rich Man</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> in this World: But we read alſo of the Happineſs of the one, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of the other, as ſoon as they died. The Comforts of the one, and the Torments of the other, were doubtleſs unexpreſſibly great, tho
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102130:8"/>we may allow an Addition to both, upon the Re-union of Body and Soul at the Reſurrection of the Dead. But more particularly,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Souls of good Men at Death, enter into a ſtate of Reſt, Happineſs and Bliſs. That of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> being carried into <hi>Abraham's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. xviii. 11.</note> The meaning of that Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion our Saviour ſeems to interpret in another place, when he ſays, <hi>Many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, and ſit down with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac and Jacob in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven.</hi> Alluding to a Feaſt, where the Gueſts ſat ſo, as to be half kneeling, and the moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable place was to be next to that of the Maſter, to lie as it were in his Boſom. As is ſaid of the Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Diſciple concerning Chriſt. If it denote an eminent degree of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs in Heaven, it infers a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſtate of Happineſs after Death; called the <hi>Boſom of Abraham,</hi> rather than of <hi>Adam, Enoch</hi> or <hi>Noah,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Promiſes were eſpecially
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102130:9"/>made to him; and to his Seed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd the Covenant and the Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And he is propounded as a Pattern of Faith and Obedience, and called, <hi>the Friend of God,</hi> and <hi>the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Faithful:</hi> And they who imitate him, ſhall be gathered into <hi>his Boſom,</hi> and be made partakers of Bleſſedneſs and Glory with him. This is called <hi>Paradiſe</hi> by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our:
<note place="margin">Luk. xxiii. 43.</note> And we learn from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where this Paradiſe is, even in <hi>the third Heavens.</hi> The Ancients call the Place and State before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, <hi>The Porch of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, the Courts of the Lord, the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Seats, or Tabernacles of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Place of Refreſhment, the Reſt of Security, an Habitation with God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From what our Saviour ſaid to <hi>the Penitent Thief</hi> on the Croſs, and from what we may gather from this Parable concerning <hi>Lazarus;</hi> the Immediate Happineſs of the Souls of Good Men in another ſtate is affirmed. That they are not to tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102130:9"/>for their Felicity till the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.
<note place="margin">Acts vii. 59.</note> So when the Body of <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> falls aſleep, the Lord Jeſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his Spirit. And the Apoſtle deſires to be uncloath'd of this Earthly Tabernacle,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. v 8.</note>
               <note place="margin">1 John iv. 17.</note> that his Soul might enter into the Houſe not made with Hands. That he might be <hi>preſent with the Lord.</hi> He deſir'd to be diſſolved, that he might <hi>be with Chriſt,</hi> as what was far better; <hi>(much more better.)</hi> And the ſame Phraſe, <hi>being with Chriſt,</hi> or being <hi>preſent with him,</hi> is us'd for the Happineſs of the Saints <hi>after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ iv. 14, 17.</note> intimating that it is the ſame ſort of Happineſs, and is ſo much preferrable to any preſent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God in this World, that this is call'd <hi>an Abſence from him.</hi> We likewiſe read of the Souls of the Martyrs, who came out of great Tribulation, and had waſhed their Robes, and made them white in the Blood of the Lamb,
<note place="margin">Rev. vii. 14.</note> 
               <hi>That they are before the Throne of God, ſerving him in his Temple:</hi> And that is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102130:10"/>of his <hi>Immediate Preſence</hi> in Another Place, for the <hi>Lord God Almighty,
<note place="margin">Chap. xxi. 22.</note> and the Lamb are ſaid to be the Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How excellent a Change will Death make upon the Soul's leaving the Body? If it paſs into a Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Paradiſe, and hear a Voice from him that ſits upon the Throne, <hi>Enter into thy Maſter's Joy.</hi> Poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> was lately very miſerable at the Rich Man's Door; now ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry happy in <hi>Abraham's Boſom:</hi> Lately cover'd with Sores and Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; now cloathed with Glory: Lately pining with Hunger; now all his Wants are ſupplied. His extream Poverty made him the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day deſpiſed by the Rich Man; he could find no Entrance at his Gates, no Admiſſion, no Relief; but now he is envy'd for his Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The difference which depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Souls will feel of their Happy State, from what they lately were, and the Senſe they have of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils they are Deliver'd from, will
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102130:10"/>give an Accent to their Happineſs. The freſh Remembrance of what they were in this World, will help their Joyfull Senſe of the Happy Change: And to compare their own Condition with that of Loſt, Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Souls: To think of the Hell they deſerv'd, and others ſuffer; and they themſelves did ſometime fear; and compare it with the Reſt, and Peace, and Joy, and Glory that they now partake of, will add to their Felicity. And who can tell how great that is, even before the Reſurrection? <hi>For eye hath not ſeen,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. ii. 9.</note> nor ear heard, nor hath it entred into the heart of man to conceive, what God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> It is repreſented in Scripture by, and above all ſuch Pleaſures as do moſt ſenſibly Delight us, to ſet forth the Joys of Heaven to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable and full of Glory. When the Divine Image ſhall be perfected, the Body of Sin and Death removed, all our Darkneſs, Impurity, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption healed. And if there were
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102130:11"/>nothing elſe, but a perfect and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Freedom and Deliverance from Sin, with all the Cauſes, Concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and Effects of it, they to whom it is now the greateſt Burden, Trouble, and Sorrow, muſt account it an Unſpeakable Felicity.</p>
            <p>But the Soul ſhall then awake as out of Sleep, to ſee and know things as really they are, and be in a ſtate of more vigorous Activity than while it animated the Body: But what the Bleſſedneſs will be, of <hi>Faith</hi> turned into <hi>Viſion,</hi> (when all the Powers of the Soul are enlarged, raiſed, and ſuited to the views of God's Glory by Chriſt, and made more receptive of Divine Communications) is what we want Words to deſcribe, and can think, and ſpeak of, but very imperfectly. For now we ſee thro' a Glaſs darkly, but hereafter Face to Face, without interruption or obſcurity. This we know that they ſhall not only eſcape the Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Hell, but enter into a ſtate of Happineſs, the Joy of their Lord.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102130:11"/>We read of Glory to be revealed <hi>in them,</hi> and Glory conferred <hi>on them.</hi> In general, as to real and poſitive Bleſſedneſs for the Souls of Good Men after Death, even before the Day of Judgement, we have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Teſtimony of Scripture, but ſomewhat from the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> How<hi>'s Bleſſedneſs of the Righteous,</hi> Chap. 10.</note>. All the Philoſophers who believ'd the Immortality of the Soul (and how few but did allow it?) they profeſs to believe the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Souls of Good Men in ſeparation from the Body: for knowing nothing of the Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Body, they could not dream of a ſleeping Interval, till the Day of Judgment.</p>
            <p>The like we may ſay of a ſtate of poſtitive Miſery for wicked Souls af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death. Here in this parable is a Loſt Soul condemn'd to Torment, aſſoon as departed this Life, before the Reſurrection. And Torments ſo extream, as that the moſt incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Refreſhment would be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon'd a great Relief. The Diſcourſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102130:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>is fram'd according to the Nature of a Parable between the <hi>Rich Man</hi> in Hell, and <hi>Abraham</hi> in Heaven, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> with him. How fain would he now change Conditions with the Beggar, whom he neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and deſpiſed at his Door! What would he give to be comforted as he is! But <hi>he lift up his Eyes in Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> unexpreſſible Torment; and ſo the Scriptures every where repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it.
<note place="margin">Rom. ii. 8.</note> 'Tis call'd <hi>Indignation and Anguiſh, Tribulation and Wrath. 'Tis a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God.
<note place="margin">Pſal. xi. 6.</note> He will wound the Head of his Enemies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. lxviii. 21.</note> We read of a <hi>Lake of Fire,</hi> a <hi>Lake of Brimſtone,</hi> a <hi>Furnace of Fire,</hi> of <hi>tearing in pieces, cutting in pieces, dividing in the midſt, drowning in Perdition,</hi> of being <hi>bound hand and foot and caſt into Fire to be burnt,</hi> of <hi>outer darkneſs, chains of darkneſs, the great Winepreſs of the wrath of God,</hi> &amp;c. Be ſure the Sufferings of the wicked in the other World are greater than we can endure for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102130:12"/>God in this, otherwiſe the threatning of ſuch a Puniſhment would not be an effectual reſtraint from Sin. But how extream muſt be that Puniſhment, ſet forth by the violence of Fire enraged with Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and prepared by the wrath of God, for the Devil and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? And the Sting of a guilty, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Conſcience, as the biting and gnawing of a Worm, on the moſt tender part? 'Tis repreſented in ſuch a manner as is moſt proper to impreſs the quickeſt ſenſe of terrour on our minds; to ſtrike our Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with the Extremity, as well as the Reality of thoſe Sufferings. And if the Expreſſions be but Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical, they make the Torments the greater, as intimating rather that they are but faintly ſhadow'd by what is moſt grievous in this World.</p>
            <p>We read of being tormented in Flames, and yet of Darkneſs. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Fire,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr.</hi> Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot<hi>'s Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1700. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of difficult Texts.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad. 11 § 6.</note> 
               <hi>Outer Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> The fearfull ſtate of Sinners
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102130:13"/>under the Wrath of God deſcrib'd by both. We read that the <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> under the plague of Darkneſs, <hi>ſaw not one another, neither aroſe any from his place,</hi> Ex. x. 23. This the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> gives an account of in theſe terms, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88.49. <hi>He caſt upon them the fierceneſs of his Anger, Wrath, and Indignation, by ſending evil Angels among them.</hi> The Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of God without any beam or ſpark of his Favour is <hi>Darkneſs</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. And the Devils may rage, and roar, and terrify, and yet Sinners be held in Chains of Darkneſs, that they cannot ſtir.</p>
            <p>God is repreſented as <hi>a Conſuming Fire,
<note place="margin">Heb. xii. ult.</note> a Devouring Fire,</hi> and Sinners fall into his hands as an Avenging Judge.
<note place="margin">Iſa. xxxiii. 14</note> We read of his <hi>Fiery Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> to devour his Adverſaries, of <hi>his Wrath</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> to be <hi>made known,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. ix. 22.</note> and <hi>glorified</hi> in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And <hi>who knows the Power of his Anger?</hi> ſaid <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Man of God, who ſaw his Glory. The <hi>Wrath of God</hi> is the Hell of Devils,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102130:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>and of all the Damned. If he be angry but a little, we can't ſtand, <hi>at the rebuke of his Countenance we periſh;</hi> what then if he ſtir up all his Wrath, in the day of his fierce Anger, when he comes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute Judgment and to render Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, from the Glory of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, upon the Wicked fitted for, and reſerved to Deſtruction?</p>
            <p>You may fancy the moſt terrible things can be dreaded; of Fire and Brimſtone, Wracks and Tempeſts, boiling Pitch, ſcalding Lead, or a burning Furnace, and being kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live for a long time to ſuffer ſuch exquiſite pains: But all we can hereby reach to conceive, of the Pains of Hell, falls as much ſhort of the Torments of the Damned, as one little ſpark of Fire on the hand, compared with the furious rage of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Furnace, heated ſeven times hotter than ordinary. 'Tis impoſſible for the moſt awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Conſcience to conceive the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102130:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Horrour of it. Who can tell how God can puniſh, or what the guilty Soul can be made to ſuffer under the Wrath of a provoked God! when he comes to be revenged for all his abuſed Mercies, for all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his Authority; when he will ſhew forth his Wrath. <hi>Oh! fear him, who after he hath killed the Body, hath power to caſt Soul and Body into Hell.</hi> 
               <q>We have heard, (as
<note n="*" place="margin">J. Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Heavenly Glory,</hi> Ch. xi. 8vo. <hi>lately prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
                  </note> one expreſſes it) of ſome who have endured breaking on the Wheel, ripping up of their Bowels, fleaing alive, racking of Joynts, burning of Fleſh, pound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Mortar, tearing in pieces with Fleſh-hooks, boyling in Oyl, roaſting on hot fiery Grid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>irons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet all theſe, tho' you ſhould ſuperad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Diſeaſes, ſuch as the Plague, Stone, Gout, Strangury, or whatever elſe you can name moſt torturing to the Body; together with the moſt Inhumane Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102130:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>prodigious Butcheries, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the moſt bloody Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors upon the Martyrs of Chriſt in any Age, they would all come infinitely ſhort (tho' they were all collected into one extreameſt Torment) of that Wrath, that Horror, that unconceivable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh which the Damned muſt inevitably ſuffer every Moment, without any Intermiſſion of their Pains, in Helliſh Flames.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What a terrible change muſt Death then make in one that <hi>fared deliciouſly every Day,</hi> and was cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in <hi>Purple and fine Linnen</hi> (his Winter and Summer Garment,) to be ſtript of all his pleaſant things? To be reduc'd to the greateſt Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as in one Moment to ſink from an Earthly Paradiſe into a Lake of Fire: After ſo much Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Abundance, Luxury and Superfluity, to awake in Flames, to want a drop of Water to cool his Tongue. The Poor Man ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102130:15"/>in vain for Relief from him a little while ago, but now he begs ſome Relief of the Poor Man. <hi>Father Abraham, have Mercy upon me, and ſend Lazarus, that he may dip the tip of his Finger in Water, and cool my Tongue. Son, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that thou in thy Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time hadſt thy good things, but La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus evil things; but now he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted and thou art tormented.</hi> What's become of his delicate Wines, and various Diſhes, his rich Ornaments, numerous Attendants, and all the Particulars that went to accommodate his Pomp and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and maintain his Luxurious Living? Now he is dead he <hi>lifts up his Eyes in Torment.</hi> What a terrible change will it be for one that in this World was Loved, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs'd, Reſpected, liv'd in Plenty and Abundance, and wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to eat, drink, and be merry? <hi>What a Change,</hi> for ſuch a one to die, and his Soul awake in Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments!
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102130:15"/>At the very moment that ſhe leaves the Body, to find ſhe's extreamly miſerable, and loſt for ever, ſeparated from all the Good ſhe loved and delighted in, and plung'd into an Abyſs of unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Miſery.</p>
            <p>The Remembrance of good things paſt, will make the Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Evil to be much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable. There is much of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the remembrance of their paſt Enjoyments and Actions: what they have had, and what they have done, and what they have loſt: To remember how fair they once ſtood for Heaven; but forfeited, neglected and deſpiſed it: The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their paſt Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities which are gone, will be their Torment: If they could never think of the paſt Mercies of God, or of the Grace, and Love of Chriſt, that called them to Repentance, and offered them Salvation, it would eaſe and mitigate a great part
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102130:16"/>of their Torment: Whereas they ſhall know, and remember, and think of it; how they were called, adviſed, and warned: But there was ſome Trifle which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd before Heaven: They ſhall be convinc'd, fully convinc'd, that they deſerve all the Miſeries they ſuffer, and have none to blame but themſelves: That 'tis juſt with God to baniſh them from Heaven, out of the Region of Light and Joy: And this they ſhall reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to their unſpeakable Anguiſh; for the knowledge of the Soul will be more clear, and lively, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, when ſeparated from the Body: And accordingly, the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Soul will be more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and impetuous. Their Eyes ſhall be opened, and the Vail upon their Hearts removed: Their Sins ſhall be ſet in order before them; and they ſhall know, how much God hates Sin, and what is the Obliquity, Deformity, and Injuſtice
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102130:16"/>of it: What Oppoſition to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of God; and what Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude for all his Mercies, is included in it; with all the other Aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Guilt; as againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Convictions, Promiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And they ſhall not be able to forget any thing of this; or to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves one moment from ſuch thoughts. They ſhall ſee nothing, and think of nothing but what ſhall afflict them. They ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member for what momentary Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, they loſt the Joys of Heaven, and are driven from the preſence of the Lord. What plain warnings they once had, but they would not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken nor conſider. As is according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly threatned, Iſa. LXV. 12, 13, 14. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when I called ye did not anſwer, but did evil before mine eyes; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold my Servants ſhall eat and drink, but ye ſhall be hungry and thirſty. Behold my Servants ſhall rejoyce, but ye ſhall be aſhamed. Behold my Servants ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102130:17"/>ſing for joy of Heart, but ye ſhall cry for ſorrow of Heart, and ſhall howl for vexation of Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Extremity of their Sufferings, we read, that <hi>they ſhall gnaw their Tongue for pain, and blaſpheme the God of Heaven becauſe of their pains,</hi> Rev. xvi. 10, 11. You may judge a little of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of their Sufferings by what we have heard or ſeen of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of a Diſtreſſed Conſcience, when but a Spark of the Divine Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure falls on the Soul: how Confounded and Amazed, how Reſtleſs and Terrify'd are Men in ſuch a Caſe? when they ſhall cry out,
<note place="margin">Pſalm lxxviii. 6.7, 15, 16, 17. Job xvi. 12, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Thy Wrath lies hard upon me: thy fierce Wrath goeth over me: While I ſuffer thy Terrors, I am di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, and ready to die.</hi> It is not poſſible fully to underſtand, what Fears and Agonies, what Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, what Horror, what Deſpair that Man muſt feel within himſelf, who apprehends his Soul is loſt,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102130:17"/>or like to be loſt. For the real Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Immortality of the Soul, with ſome awakened Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God's deſerved, threatned Vengeance, when brought home to a Man's own particular caſe, muſt needs diſtreſs him, and fill him with Amazement. What can you ſpeak to him, or what can be done for him, to give him Eaſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further than you can give him Hope? 'Tis an Evidence that this is little believed and conſidered, becauſe there are no more who cry out in ſuch Terror and Diſtreſs of Soul. But ſeveral under the ſenſe of one Sin have been perplexed in Conſcience, ſo as to be in Danger of Deſtroying themſelves, and of being ſwallowed up in Deſpair. God can ſet it on with ſuch a ſenſe of Guilt, that ſhall rend the Heart in pieces with the moſt deſperate Rage, and none of the Pleaſures of Senſe, no Muſick, no merry Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, no nor the Spirits of Wine,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102130:18"/>ſhall be able to ſtifle the Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or cure the Fears, or ſilence the Reflections of an accuſing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: Which can make a Man ſo very miſerable, as to wiſh he had never been, or that he might ceaſe to be; or that he might be any other Creature. Nay, ſome have wiſh'd that they were rather in Hell than in their preſent Horror. And if it may be thus for
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> one Sin: Oh! what reſtleſs Anguiſh? what intolerable Wrath? what gnaſhing of Teeth? what gnawing of Conſcience? what deſpairing Roarings? what horrible Torments may every Impenitent Sinner ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, when the whole black, and bloody Catalogue of all his Sins, ſhall be marſhal'd together at once againſt him, and every one keen'd with as much torturing Fury, as the infinite Anger of Almighty God can put into it, after that he hath with incorrigible Stubbornneſs out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Day of his gracious Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102130:18"/>If a little Senſe of God's Wrath hath ſuch direful Effects in this World, what will it be, when all his Waves ſhall go over them? Now they may ſip a little drop of the bitter Cup; they may taſte a little of the uppermoſt part of it; and they can't live under this; what will it be in Hell to drink the Dregs of that Cup of Trembling?</p>
            <p>You may gueſs ſomewhat by what <hi>Francis Spira</hi> ſaid in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing Anguiſh, under the Guilt of his Apoſtaſie. <q>
                  <hi>Oh! that I were gone from hence! Oh! that ſome body would let out this weary Soul! Never was Man alive, a Spectacle of ſuch Miſery! I feel God's heavy Anger; it burns like the Torments of Hell within me; and afflicts my Soul with Pains unutterable. Verily Deſperation is Hell it ſelf. — The Damned in Hell, I think, endure not the like Miſery.</hi>
               </q>— He being ſound in his Mind and Memory, he yet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102130:19"/>wiſhed to be in the caſe of <hi>Cain,</hi> 
               <q>or <hi>Judas.— Oh,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if I could but conceive the leaſt ſpark of Hope in my Breaſt of a better ſtate hereafter, I would not refuſe to bear the moſt heavy wrath of the great God for two thouſand Years, ſo that at length I might get out of miſery— Oh! that God would let looſe his hand upon me! I would ſcorn the threats of the moſt cruel Tyrant, and bear Torments with the moſt invincible Reſolution, and glory in the outward Profeſſion of Chriſt, till I were choakt with the Flame, and my Body burnt to aſhes.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>You may have now, a wounded Spirit, and an uneaſie Conſcience, but a plentifull Eſtate, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Friends, and many other things to leſſen your burden. The Arrows of the Almighty ſtrike now but one part, and not all: But when all thy Sins ſhall be ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before thee, and God ſhall ſtir
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102130:19"/>up all his wrath, thy Terrour, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs and Anguiſh, without any thing to alleviate or abate it, will be unexpreſſible, and unſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us now conſider that both theſe States of Happineſs and Miſery are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable</hi> and <hi>Everlaſting.</hi> The ſtate of <hi>Lazarus</hi> in Bleſſedneſs, and of the Rich Man in Torment, were neither of them to be alter'd. <hi>There is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable Gulf fixt by the Eternal Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and irrevocable Decree of God.</hi> That the Damned ſhall never aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to Heaven, nor the Bleſſed ever ſink into Hell. The Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the one, and the Felicity of the other ſhall never ceaſe! 'Tis <hi>Everlaſting Life;</hi> 'tis <hi>Everlaſting Deſtruction.</hi> The whole Frame of the Chriſtian Religion is built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Truth, That Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality are brought to light by the Goſpel, as to the Bleſſedneſs or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102130:20"/>Miſery after Death. We muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our Chriſtianity, and throw up our Bibles, condemn the Son of God for an Impoſtor, and the Holy Scriptures for a Fable, and all the wiſeſt men that have ever been in the World, as Fools, for believing the Goſpel of Chriſt, if there be not two Eternal States, of Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Miſery after Death. Our Lord's account of the proceedings of the Laſt Day,
<note place="margin">Matt. xxv.</note> and the Iſſue of the Final Judgment is expreſs in this matter. And it is called <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Judgment,</hi> Heb. vi. 2. Not for the continuance of its Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but in regard of the Effects and Conſequences of it: For tho' we know not how long the Day of Judgment will laſt, yet the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to follow, of Eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and Puniſhments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> As to the Bleſſedneſs of the Saints. <hi>They that would paſs from us to you cannot,</hi> ſaith <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102130:20"/>Not that any would chuſe for one hour to be abſent from God in Heaven, if they might; but upon ſuppoſition they would, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. If <hi>Abraham</hi> had deſired <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> had been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, yet <hi>the Gulf was fixt:</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly we read of <hi>Everlaſting Life,
<note place="margin">Joh. vi. 27.40.47, 51, 54, 58. Ch. viii. 51 Ch. xi. 26. Heb. xiii. 14. 2 Cor v. 1. Heb ix. 5. 1 Pet. i. 4. 2 Pet i 11. Rev xxi. 4. 1 Cor. xv. 57.</note> Eternal Glory, Eternal Salvation, an Eternal Inheritance that fadeth not away, the Everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Everlaſting Habitations, a Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing City, a Houſe Eternal in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Pleaſures at God's Right Hand for ever.</hi> And that they that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on Chriſt ſhall <hi>never taſte Death.</hi> That <hi>they cannot dye,</hi> for they are equal to the Angels, who always behold the Face of their Heavenly Father, and abide in the Light of his Countenance. That they ſhall bear the Image of <hi>the Heavenly Adam,</hi> who ſhould never dye, and by whom at laſt, <hi>Death ſhall be ſwallowed up in victory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:102130:21"/>
            <p>After millions of Years and Ages, the Felicity of the Saints ſhall be as far from ending, as when their Souls were firſt received into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. The Infinite Love of God, the Everlaſting Merit of Chriſt, and the Unchangeableneſs of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, aſſures us they ſhall be <hi>Happy for ever.</hi> They ſhall <hi>eat of the Tree of Life,</hi> in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God;
<note place="margin">Ro iii. 12.</note> and <hi>be Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in the Divine Temple, and go out no more.</hi> To live <hi>for ever</hi> in the Light, and Love, and Joy of Heaven; Oh! what a Thought is that! How may it ſwallow up all our other Thoughts! If one day's Communion with God on Earth, be better than a thouſand elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; what ſhall we think of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate, <hi>Everlaſting</hi> Communion with God in Heaven? When we ſhall ſee him as he is, and love him more than we can now think; and that not for a Day or a Week, but for thouſands and millions of Years,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102130:21"/>yea for a long and bleſſed Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that will never be over. For it is an Immortal Inheritance, 'tis an Everlaſting Kingdom. We ſhall reign with God, and with the Lamb for ever. We ſhall ſee him, love him, praiſe him, and enjoy him for evermore. What we ſhall ſee and know, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leſſen in our Eye and Eſteem: What we ſhall love, will never ceaſe to be lovely: What we ſhall praiſe, will always deſerve our praiſe: And what we ſhall enjoy, we ſhall never be weary of enjoying: God ſhall be <hi>All in All,</hi> to fill every power and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of the Soul, that there ſhall be nothing to incline, nor cauſe a change.</p>
            <p>It is a little thing, to ſay the Bleſſedneſs and Joy of the Saints ſhall laſt as many Years, as there has been drops of Rain faln from Heaven ſince the beginning of the World: for it ſhall endure as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102130:22"/>long as there is a God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and He is the ſame who was, and is, and is to come, <hi>from Everlaſting, to Everlaſting.</hi> Our God ſhall live for ever: Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour will never die; and we ſhall live for ever, in his light, and love, and likeneſs; <hi>Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Eternity ſhall be united.</hi> How great a thing is this, to ſay my God and Saviour, and <hi>for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mine?</hi> Eternal Life is all the World in one word, and more than ten thouſand Worlds. To be ever with the Lord; to have an immovable Happineſs in the preſence of the <hi>ever-living God;</hi> To ſay, my Portion is ſure, and can never be loſt. It is <hi>mine for ever;</hi> what a glory is this! Now I may loſe my Health, or Credit, or Friends, or Life; but <hi>the Gift of God by Jeſus Chriſt is Eternal Life.</hi> Nothing ſhall ever ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate us from the Love of God in Chriſt. This is the very Spirit of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102130:22"/>Heaven, the Crown of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs of the Saints: To be for ever the objects of his Infinite Love; to enjoy a Felicity that ſhall never decay, or be diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; never be forfeited, or loſt. It will rather always encreaſe; for we cannot poſſibly know God all at once: New Beauties will ſtill diſcover themſelves in an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Object; and therefore we ſhall love him more and more, by knowing him more; and ſo our Joy will continue and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, without fear, or danger of a period: But we ſhall know, and love, and rejoyce more and more, without end. Oh! how imperfectly do our weak and ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Thoughts conceive of this Bleſſed Eternity! To be Bleſſed with the Lord in Glory, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dye: To rejoyce with Joy unſpeakable, and ever to rejoyce: To live for ever belov'd of God, and to be joyfull and happy in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102130:23"/>his Love for ever: Oh! what Hearts have we, that can admit the hopes of this, without a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport? without deſpiſing all thoſe things that people call <hi>Great</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, but are ended with us in a dying hour?
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See more on this Head,</hi> Reflections on Time and Eternity. <hi>Sect.</hi> xx.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Gulf is fixt, as to the Miſery and Torment of the Wicked. They have no Expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Releaſe; Eternal and Everlaſting are joyn'd with the Torments of Hell, as well as with the Bleſſedneſs of Heaven. <hi>Theſe ſhall go away into Everlaſting Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</hi> Though their Bodies be held Priſoners in the Grave till the Reſurrection, their Souls are in miſery, waiting for their final doom. And at the laſt day of the World, they ſhall be found in the ſame ſtate, as at the day of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102130:23"/>Death, and then be puniſh'd with Everlaſting Deſtruction. The ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Sentence is, <hi>Depart ye curſed into everlaſting Fire.</hi> This is the acknowledged Doctrin of the Chriſtian Church in all Ages, and moſt expreſsly aſſerted in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures. We read <hi>of a Worm that never dies, of a Fire that ſhall never be quenched, Everlaſting Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, Eternal Damnation, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Deſtruction; the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Darkneſs for ever; a Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone, where they ſhall be tormented Day and Night for ever and ever, and where the ſmoke of their Torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever.</hi> This Doctrin is very cunningly undermin'd by ſome, upon the account of their corrupt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and boldly deny'd by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the ſake of their ill Practices.</p>
            <p>The Adverſaries of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Satisfaction of Chriſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102130:24"/>would have the Puniſhment of the Wicked at the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to conſiſt in
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ignis Eternus in Sacris Literis vocatur, non is, in quo res ei injecta aeternum uritur, nec un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam conſumitur; ſed qui ita rem exurit ac con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumit, ut illa in Aeternum non reſtituatur in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegram; vel qui tam diu ardet, donee res illa planè &amp; in totum comburatur, ut ex eâ nihil prorſus remaneas Ita</hi> Eſai. 66. <hi>ultimo. Dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur de occiſis quod vermis eorum non morietur: nimirum ſicut vermis, qui in cadavere alique naſcitur, tamdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vivit, nec moritur donec cada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fuerit prorſus abſumptum. Vide</hi> Marc. 9.44. <hi>Videtur haec locutio ſumpta ex</hi> Eſai. 34.9, 10. <hi>ubi Propheta divina judicia Idumaeis intermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Mutabuntur torrentes ejus in picem, <hi>&amp; terra ejus in Sulphur, eritque Terra ejus pro Pice ardente, noctu &amp; interdiu non extinguetur: in ſeculum aſcendet Fumus ejus.</hi> Crellii <hi>Comment. in Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; Comment. in</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ut vero Deus in omnibus juſtitiae tenax eſt, ita hic quoque ſuper neminem extendet panam meritis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>jus majorem. Nullà autem poſſunt eſſe peccata <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am gravia, quae ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mpiternis cruciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus poſſent aequart.</hi> Wolzogenius <hi>in Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. See more Paſſiges of this kind in Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> on the <hi>Creed,</hi> Art. XII. and Dr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> of the <hi>Socinian Creed,</hi> 8vo. <hi>Chap</hi> V.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Annihilation,</hi> a total and eternal Diſſolution of their Perſons; that they ſhall be eternally deſtroyed, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſo as to exiſt no more.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102130:24"/>Whereas the Scriptures ſets forth the Miſery of Sinners in the next World, under ſuch Expreſſions as plainly denote the Exiſtence of the Sufferers. Would any one deſcribe <hi>Annihilation,</hi> by being plung'd into a Lake of Fire and Brimſtone; where they ſhall have no Reſt Day nor Night for ever? The word <hi>Perdition, Deſtruction, Death,</hi> us'd for the Sufferings of the Wicked in another World, do manifeſtly import extreme Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and not Annihilation. God is ſaid to deſtroy Nations, when he brings great Calamities upon them. An Oppreſſour may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy many Perſons and Families, and yet is not ſuppoſed to Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate them. The Prodigal is ſaid to <hi>periſh for Hunger,</hi> tho' he were yet alive. So for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>loſing the Soul;</hi> for a Man to loſe his Soul, is to periſh eternally in the other World, in our Saviour's ſenſe of that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102130:25"/>
               <hi>Matt. XVI.</hi> 26. <hi>What ſhall it profit a Man to gain the World, and loſe his Soul?</hi> The word we render <hi>loſe,</hi> ſignifies to have a Mulct inflicted on him: to loſe it in a way of Puniſhment, to be puniſh'd in his Soul: And 'tis brought in as an Argument, why a Man ſhould not fear Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Death; but lay down his Life, when our Saviour calls him to it: Becauſe if he ſhould ſave his Life, and yet loſe his Soul, as to the other World, though he gain'd as much as can be ſuppos'd of this World; He would be a miſerable Creature, and make a fooliſh Bargain. To underſtand the loſing of the Soul, only of a Temporal Death, would be to deſtroy the Argument which our Lord brings it for: yea it would be a Reaſon againſt their doing that, which in the foregoing Verſe he tells them they ought to do, even lay down their Lives for him.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:102130:25"/>
            <p>As to the Expreſſions, <hi>The Wrath of God abideth on him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. iii. 36.</note> and <hi>he ſhall not ſee Life,</hi> which are likewiſe objected; I would ask, How can the Wrath of God be executed, ſo as to abide on One who hath no Exiſtence, but is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilated? Their abiding under Wrath, doth not deny, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Exiſtence, and Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in Being. So of that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,
<note place="margin">Matth. iii. 12.</note> 
               <hi>the Chaff ſhall be burnt up with unquenchable Fire:</hi> for if the burning this Chaff be to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and annihilate it, why is it by a Fire that cannot be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? when it has done its work, it ſhould be put out.</p>
            <p>Beſides, To ſuppoſe the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhall be Annihilated at the Day of Judgment, is to <hi>equal all Sinners,</hi> as to any Puniſhment af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Day of Judgment, for one Man cannot be <hi>more Annihilated</hi> than another. Whereas the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is expreſs, That <hi>it ſhall be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102130:26"/>more tolerable in the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for ſome, than for others.</hi> Yea this would infer a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt <hi>Inequality of Puniſhment:</hi> for then the caſe of thoſe who died in their Sins at the beginning of the World, would be very hard in compariſon of ſuch as died to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of it. Suppoſe one died the laſt year, or month, before Chriſt's Coming, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that died in his Sins before the Flood; the former, (I ſuppoſe the greater Criminal,) would come to an end of his Sufferings in a very ſhort time; whereas the other, (and ſuppoſe a leſs Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,) who died in the beginning of the World, has been ſuffering the Wrath of God for ſome thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Years. If the Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Wicked at the Day of Judgment be Annihilation, what account can be given of this Ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of Puniſhment?</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:102130:26"/>
            <p>But the <hi>Endleſs Miſery</hi> of the Wicked in another World, is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively affirmed by our Saviour no leſs than <hi>five times</hi> in <hi>ſix Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> of one Chapter; <hi>Mark IX.</hi> 43-48. and in many other places. Not only is <hi>the Fire</hi> ſaid to be <hi>Everlaſting,</hi> where they ſhall be tormented; and ſo Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely Everlaſting, as <hi>never to be quenched:</hi> But ſo certain that it ſhall never be quenched, that <hi>the Smoke thereof ſhall aſcend for ever and ever.</hi> The Sentence of their Condemnation will never be reverſt: Their Condition is never to be alter'd; but their Torments will be endleſs, and their Miſery eternal.</p>
            <p>If you believe the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the Goſpel-Revelation concerning the Deſign of Chriſt's Coming into the World to ſave Sinners from future Wrath, you will leſs wonder, that they, who deny the Divinity of Chriſt, ſhould
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102130:27"/>endeavour to put out the Fire of Hell, and make the Eternal Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Sinners a meer Fiction. For what need of the Son of God to come from Heaven, and take our Nature, and dye for our Sins, <hi>to deliver us from Wrath to come;</hi> if there be no ſuch Wrath to come after the Day of Judgment? There is reaſon to fear, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who hearken to the <hi>Socinian</hi> Principles, as to Chriſt's Deity and Satisfaction, little know the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of their Doctrine. For what can the ſcoffing Atheiſt deſire more, than to loſe his Being for ever; ſince an happy one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, he does not expect? If the profeſſed Belief of what the Scriptures ſo plainly ſpeak, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Torments of Hell, hath no more Influence to reſtrain men from Sin; but the World be ſtill ſo bad, how much worſe would it be, if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all of this to be fear'd?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102130:27"/>'Tis manifeſt that the Providence of God in all Ages, has made uſe of this Doctrine to preſerve Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society from ruine, by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Wickedneſs. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that would take away this Fence, and deliver Mankind from theſe Fears, as groundleſs and unreaſonable, do moſt effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſerve the Deſign of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, to promote Senſuality and Licentiouſneſs, and turn ſerious Religion out of the World. For 'tis found by Experience, that the Promiſe of the Heavenly Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity does not ſo much affect us, as threatned Damnation. 'Tis to eſcape the Latter, men are brought to conſider the Certainty and Greatneſs of the Former: And it is one of the great Motives made uſe of in the Goſpel to reſtrain Men from Wickedneſs, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken them to give all Diligence to work out their own Salvation; but if they were once ſet free
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102130:28"/>from the Fear, and Belief of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Puniſhments, one of the moſt powerfull Reſtraints from Sin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Motives to Religion is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd.</p>
            <p>But there are Others who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this Doctrine, becauſe a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Life hath made it their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to do ſo. They deſire to follow their Pleaſures without being diſturbed by any ſuch Fear, and ſo would fain perſwade themſelves, that there will be no ſuch <hi>Everlaſting Hell</hi> hereafter: Nay, there be many who have made bold with Conſcience, and contracted ſuch Guilt, that if the Holy Scripture be true, they muſt be undone in another World: And are forc'd to flee to Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or Socinianiſm, as a Refuge after Shipwrack; to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves eaſie, or at leaſt to leſſen their Fears, when they think of dying. And who doth not know what a Byaſs upon Men's Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102130:28"/>Intereſt, and Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will caſt? How eaſily do we believe what we deſire ſhould be true? and how hardly are we perſwaded of the Truth of that, which in its Conſequences ſpeaks Terror to our own Caſe? But whatever ſhifts any ſuch may make for a little while, to keep Conſcience quiet, they will find e're long to their Eternal Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, all their little Cavils and Objections anſwered, if they will not <hi>now</hi> conſider things in order to their Conviction.</p>
            <p>Did they better know <hi>the Evil of Sin,</hi> and the Infinite Majeſty and Glory, Purity and Juſtice, Authority, and Soveraignty of GOD, who is Deſpiſed, Affront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Diſobeyed by Sinners; they would ſooner underſtand the weakneſs of their Pleas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtian Faith. They would not lay ſo much ſtreſs on what they pretend; That they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102130:29"/>would not ſerve any of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies in ſuch a manner, if it were in their Power: They ſay they would not puniſh any Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Affronts againſt them, at that Rate, as we ſuppoſe God threatens to do. No, ſurely they ought not: For what is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, Affront, and Injury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Weak, Periſhing, Sinful Worm, compar'd with Obſtinate and continued Contempt of GOD? The Glorious and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Majeſty of Heaven and Earth? Have you any ſuch Dominion and Soveraignty over your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? Any ſuch Propriety in them, and Right to their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Can you Challenge that from them, which God may De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of us? Have you ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged them with any ſuch Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, as he hath loaded us withall? It is from ſlight Thoughts of <hi>the Evil of Sin,</hi> againſt <hi>the Holy Ever-Bleſſed GOD</hi> that makes us think
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102130:29"/>it hard for GOD to puniſh finally Obſtinate Rebels, with Everlaſting Wrath. We ſhould rather be Thankfull that he hath ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully warn'd us of it, and bid us to fear him, who is able to caſt Body and Soul into Hell. And by how much the more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and ſevere ſuch threatned Puniſhment is, ſo much the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is GOD to give ſuch repeated warning of it; and ſo much the more Inexcuſable are Sinners, that will not conſider it, and lay it to Heart.</p>
            <p>'Tis from Ignorance of GOD, and how much he is above us, that they dare talk ſo boldly of <hi>Divine Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs:</hi> And declare that the Everlaſting Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Wicked is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with <hi>either,</hi> or <hi>both.</hi> GOD knows better than we, what it is to be <hi>Juſt;</hi> and what is Conſiſtent with his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy.</hi> His Word is expreſs and plain
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102130:30"/>concerning the State of Sinners, when the Day of Mercy is ended. The meaſure of Puniſhment with reſpect to Crimes, is not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken alway from the Quality and Degree of the Offence, much leſs from the Time and Duration of it, but from the Ends and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Government, to deter men from the Breach of the Law. The greateſt Sins may often be committed in a ſhort ſpace of Time, as <hi>Murder.</hi> So that to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue from the Diſproportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Temporary Sins, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Puniſhment, will not conclude againſt the Juſtice of GOD. Can we think, that God would threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sinners with a Puniſhment, he could not inflict without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice? Cannot GOD be Juſt, and Good, and Merciful, except he ſave the Wilful and Diſobedient, who continue to deſpiſe the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers of his Grace, and perſiſt in their Contempt and Rebellion to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102130:30"/>the very laſt? Hath he not told us, how far his Mercy ſhall reach? Thouſands of Holy Souls ſhall know to their Eternal Comfort, that GOD is infinitely Good, tho' he render Vengeance on them, that ſlighted his Mercy, and died without Repentance? They had a time of tryal: Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was offered them: They were entreated to accept it: GOD waited with much Long-ſuffering and Patience; and often renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Calls, and Warnings, and Invitations, to perſwade them to flee from Wrath to come: But they would not accept his Mercy in time.</p>
            <p>If they plead that the endleſs Puniſhment of Sinners doth not anſwer the proper Ends, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Puniſhment, <hi>viz.</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Sinner, or to admoniſh, and warn others againſt the like Offence. It muſt be conſidered, That this is not all the End and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102130:31"/>Deſign of Puniſhment: But that when God hath declared his Will to puniſh, one great End of that Puniſhment, is to vindicate his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as Governour of the World, that is injured and affronted by the Sins of Men: And there's a great deal of difference between the Ends of Puniſhment in this Life, which very much reſpect the Community, and thoſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World. And yet even <hi>here,</hi> God as the Governour of the World, may vindicate the Rites of his Honour and Soveraignty, by inflicting Puniſhment: But in the next Life, they who are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed are Obſtinate Offenders, that would not take warning, or be reclaim'd by all the Mercies and Judgments of God, either as to others, or themſelves.</p>
            <p>Moreover ſuppoſing the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the Soul; and the remaining Wickedneſs and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence of Sinners; (and Death
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102130:31"/>will not change the ill Temper and Diſpoſition of Men's Minds, but they that were filthy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy will be ſtill ſo, as well as they that were Unrighteous and Unjuſtify'd.) A ſinful Soul, if it be Immortal, muſt needs be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably miſerable. He will never Repent; there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Mercy to encourage it: And therefore, if he ſhall never die, he muſt be miſerable for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And what reaſon is there to expect, that God ſhould Annihilate thoſe that are incurably Wicked? eſpecially when he has ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly declared the contrary,
<note place="margin">Matt. xxv. ult.</note> and <hi>in the ſame Terms</hi> expreſs'd the Duration of the Puniſhment of the Wicked, as the Everlaſting Life, and Happineſs of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. <hi>Of the many that ſleep in the Duſt, ſome ſhall awake and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe to Everlaſting Life, and others to Shame, and Everlaſting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. xii 2.</note> There cannot be Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102130:32"/>Shame, and Everlaſting Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, without the Everlaſting Exiſtence of the Perſons. How can they continue for ever under Shame and Contempt, unleſs they continue in their Being?</p>
            <p>Let us therefore urge this upon our Minds and Hearts, as what we ought to believe, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider, and therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of replying againſt God, whoſe Terrors ſhould make us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, and whoſe Truth endures for ever, let us think of it in time, and put the Queſtions to our ſelves, we often meet with in the Scripture, which can never be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. <hi>Who can ſtand before him, when he is angry? Can thy Hands be ſtrong, or thy Heart en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, when he ſhall execute Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance? Who can dwell with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Fire? Who can dwell with Everlaſting Burnings?</hi> Can You, or You? You, who have lived in Eaſe and Pleaſure all your Days;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102130:32"/>and by a ſharp fit of Pain but for one half Hour, would groan as if your Hearts would break; could you abide <hi>Everlaſting Fire?</hi> An Everlaſting Toothach, Stone, or Cholick, or a much leſs Pain, but ſuppos'd Endleſs, is inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, what then is Hell! However you may ask <hi>another Queſtion,</hi> which, bleſſed be God, may be Reſolv'd, and that is, <hi>What ſhall we do to be ſaved? How ſhall we eſcape this Intolerable and Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Wrath?</hi> And this brings me to the <hi>Application,</hi> by Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Truth and Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'Tis then obvious, that <hi>Now or Never</hi> is the ſeaſon to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for <hi>Eternity,</hi> ſeeing both States are unchangeable after Death. The Gulf will then be fix'd, there is no Poſſibility for Repentance, or hope of Pardon beyond the Grave; 'twill be in vain to cry with the Fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102130:33"/>
               <hi>Lord open to us,</hi> when the Door is ſhut. Now you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to pray for Mercy, earneſtly invited, and entreated to work out your own Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and warn'd of your Danger: Now is your time to hearken to good Counſel. Many of you have miſpent a great part of your Life paſt; you ſhall not live it over again: You are not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Future: You may be in an Unchangeable State e're you are aware; ſo that to defer it one Week or Day longer, may be your undoing. You have now a Promiſe of Forgiveneſs, if you Repent, and the Hopes of God's Grace, if you ſeek it. You have yet an Opportunity to make Peace with God: This is your accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time, and Day of Salvation: The Door of Mercy, and of Hope is yet open, but e're long it will be ſhut, and your State Immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Whatever is to be done in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102130:33"/>Preparation for Eternity muſt be <hi>Now or Never.</hi> Now <hi>quickly</hi> or it <hi>will</hi> be too late; now <hi>preſently,</hi> and without Delay, or it <hi>may be</hi> too late. Is he not a bold Man that will venture to deferr, if he believes both States after Death to be Endleſs and Unchangeable? How can he be ſatisfy'd to live in ſuch a ſtate, wherein he is as near to <hi>Hell,</hi> as he is to <hi>Death?</hi> You have reaſon to be Thankful, that when others have been ſnatch'd away in their Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; <hi>Others,</hi> it may be, of your Companions, and poſſibly leſſer Sinners than you; that you are yet ſpar'd. You muſt think him to be <hi>a miſerable Man,</hi> who when he dies, ſhall be miſerable to all Eternity: And can you think him <hi>Wiſe,</hi> who will careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put it to the venture, and will not beſtirr himſelf to prevent it? Now you have, beſides the Call of God's Word, and Providence,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102130:34"/>many Helps by Friends and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ready to aſſiſt you, and the Spirit of God has not yet forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken you; but if ye will ſhut your Eyes, and ſtop your Ears, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den your Hearts, and are reſolv'd to go on; Remember you are faithfully, and plainly warned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> How valuable a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then is <hi>our Time?</hi> How great a Sin is Idleneſs, and the miſpenſe of Precious, Irrecoverable Time, on which depends our Eternal Happineſs or Miſery? What have we our Time given us for, but to provide for our Eternal State? If HEAVEN and HELL be great Realities, and no ſuch Inſignificant Words as Infidels would make them; If Endleſs Joy, or Miſery be the Conſequent of Improving, or Miſpending our Time, how ought we to value it? Within the compaſs of this little, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Time, muſt the great Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102130:34"/>be decided, where we ſhall have our Portion <hi>for ever.</hi> Doubtleſs God hath given every Man, ſufficient Work in this World for all his Time: And he that is unfit to die, or uncertain of Salvation, hath Work enough to do; and ſhould be aſhamed to live, as if he knew not what to do with his Time. Very few conſider, that of all their Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galities, this of <hi>their Time</hi> is the moſt impoſſible to be Redeem'd. And what they would give, when they come to die, for a little of that Time, that they Now are at a loſs how to throw away. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe who have left this World might have a Time of Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al again, what different Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions would they have of the value of it. But whether we Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it or no, Redeem it, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpend it; it is not long, e're we ſhall know and find, how much our preſent Time is worth.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:102130:35"/>
            <p>How many young Gentlemen, and Others, live an Idle, Senſual Life, and ſo in a Continual Courſe of Sin, againſt the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Law of God, with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of his Protection, and their Daily Bread? As if they had no Buſineſs in this World to mind, but <hi>Recreation</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure?</hi> No God to ſerve, no Soul to ſave, or Eternity to provide for? They conſider not, that it is not only Whoremongers, and Idolaters, and Drunkards, and Notorious Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals,
<note place="margin">Matt. xxv. 13. Chap. xii. 22.</note> but the <hi>Slothful and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servant,</hi> that ſhall be bound Hand and Foot, and caſt into outer Darkneſs, where ſhall be weeping and wailing, and gnaſhing of Teeth.</p>
            <p>A Life of <hi>Idleneſs</hi> is contrary to the great Ends of God, both in Creation and Redemption; for every Man is to honour God in the World, and do all the Good he can to others: To provide for
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102130:35"/>his own Salvation, and promote the Welfare of Humane Society; which can never be done by an Idle Life. And Chriſtians are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſpecial Obligation to be a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar People, zealous of good Works. Let any Man be as fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal of his Time as he can, and he will find himſelf advanc'd in Years, before he hath got a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Fitneſs for the Place and Station the Providence of God has put him in; and it may be will arrive to Old Age (if he do not die ſooner,) before he hath liv'd to any ſuch valuable Purpoſe, as by that time he will wiſh he had done.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not againſt all <hi>Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>Recreations,</hi> which, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Bounds of Moderation, are needful to keep the Body and the Mind in a due Temper for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: But too many make that a <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> which ſhould be only a <hi>Diverſion,</hi> and turn Recreation
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102130:36"/>into <hi>a Calling;</hi> by employing their whole Time in it, which is neither becoming them, as Men, or as Chriſtians. And as to Sports and Paſtimes in general, the beſt of them come ſo near to Idleneſs, and the worſt of them to Vice, that as the Latter ſhould have no part, the Other ſhould have but a ſmall Proportion of our Time, only as our Health, and fitneſs for Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs does require. For when we come to leave the World, we ſhall think otherwiſe of the value of our <hi>Haſty Time,</hi> than now we do. Then you will bitterly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the many precious Hours you ſpent in Vanity; ſaying, <q>Oh that they might be recall'd! Oh that the Opportunities of Mercy, and the Invitations of Grace that once I had, might be made me again! Oh that God would try me a little lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger! How ſtrictly and ſeriouſly would I employ my <hi>Time</hi> in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102130:36"/>Preparation for <hi>Eternity?</hi> even <hi>that Time,</hi> that I was wont to ſpend in Idleneſs and Folly, in Vain Company, and Senſual Mirth; in Chaffering for the World, or making Proviſion for the Fleſh, to fulfill the Luſts thereof! But it may be then too <hi>Late.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How Awful a thing is it, and of how great Conſequence muſt it be, for any Man <hi>to die,</hi> and leave this World? Eſpecially with what Dread ſhould we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Conſideration, of the Change by Death of one that dies in his Sins? The Apprehenſion and Thought of <hi>Death,</hi> with one of theſe two Conſequences, muſt make this Change more Affecting, Solemn, and Serious to every Conſidering Perſon, than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly it is. We hear of the Death of many; we follow ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of our Friends and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102130:37"/>to the Grave, One after A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; we talk of it in common Converſation, <hi>Such a Man is Dead; ſuch a Woman is Dead;</hi> ſuch a Relation, ſuch a Friend <hi>is Dead;</hi> but we do it oftentimes ſo ſlightly and careleſly, as if there were no more in it, than that Such and Such were gone a few Days Journey into a Neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring County; or at moſt, gone beyond Sea for a few Months: But <hi>'tis a great thing to Die, 'tis an awful thing to be Dead:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Soul muſt be ſaved or loſt <hi>for ever.</hi> Such a one <hi>is Dead.</hi> O Sirs! what is that to ſay? What do ye mean by ſuch words? Why, the Soul of ſuch a Friend or Acquaintance of mine, is gone to <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell. He</hi> or <hi>She,</hi> whom we lately convers'd with, is <hi>now</hi> unſpeakably Bleſſed, or intolerably Miſerable, and ſhall be ſo to all <hi>Eternity,</hi> according to what their State and Condition
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102130:37"/>was, when they left this World. If we miſcarry in this great Affair, and don't Die well, do not die the Death of the Righteous, we are loſt for ever. <hi>Death will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine our Everlaſting State.</hi> It is the way of all Living; the way of all the Earth: But it hath two Turnings, the one on the Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand to Everlaſting Joy and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs; the other on the Left, to Everlaſting Sorrow and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. How Serious and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant a thing then is it, for any of us, for every of us to die, if we believe the Everlaſting World, and the Conſequence of Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing!</p>
            <p>When a Man comes to die, and is apprehenſive of his Eternal State, then he cries out, <q>Oh Fool, and Wretch that I have been, to trifle away my preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Time; to forfeit all my Hopes of Heaven, by forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or contradicting the End
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102130:38"/>of Life! How madly have I ſpent my Days, without look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Endleſs World! where is now the Gain and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all my paſt Folly? What fruit have I of thoſe things, which I am now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to review, and am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to anſwer for? O that I I had liv'd in a Wilderneſs, or in Rags and Beggery, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen the Face of thoſe Companions, by whom I have been enſnar'd, ſeduc'd, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd! Oh that God would ſpare me a little longer!</q>
            </p>
            <p>How differently do the ſame Truths reliſh? What other Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions doth the view of Death give us? You may not be able upon a Bed of Sickneſs, to ſtifle or lay aſide thoſe Reflections on Religion, and another World, which now we would urge you to admit. Your Thoughts are now diverted by fond Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:102130:38"/>and Conceits, by falſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and fooliſh Hopes, by ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Delights and Recreations, by Carnal Mirth and ill-grounded Peace, and enſnaring Company: But all theſe will then have left you, to dwell alone with <hi>your Pain</hi> and <hi>your Conſcience.</hi> But how much worſe will HELL be, than a Sick-bed. You may have many things to alleviate, relieve, or aſſiſt you in this World; but Oh the Change that <hi>Death</hi> will make!</p>
            <p>The Careleſs and Secure, who now fear not the Wrath of God, dread not his Diſpleaſure, value not his Favour, matter not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be their Friend or Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; who are <hi>Stout-hearted, and far from Righteouſneſs,</hi> and under the Power of horrible Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without thoughts of an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Reckoning, and an Eternal State; who never ſay, <hi>Where is God my Maker?</hi> but live in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102130:39"/>Forgetfulneſs of him; yet when they die, their Souls re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to him, <hi>they fall into his Hands.</hi> They muſt awake, and know God, and Themſelves. They ſhall preſently have their Eyes open, and not be kept in Quiet by Ignorance, and Forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs as <hi>now;</hi> but recollect all their paſt Sins, with their Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations: Remember their paſt Mercies, with their Miſ-improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; their paſt Seaſons and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of Grace, which they have loſt: They ſhall bitterly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, charge, ſhame, and condemn themſelves, under the actual Wrath of God, for the preſent; with fearful Expectations of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and endleſs Miſery, after the final Sentence of the laſt, great Aſſize. How much better had it been for ſuch they had never been born than thus to die, and fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hands of Divine Juſtice? Better they had never liv'd in this
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102130:39"/>World. They ſhall then think ſo, and wiſh ſo; wiſh they had never been born to ſee the Light; or that they had expir'd, as ſoon as they began to breath; and had their Names enter'd into the Bills of Mortality, as ſoon as they came into the World.</p>
            <p>Such Thoughts as theſe would rectify our Judgments, cure our Vanity, and help us to overcome the World, and mortify the Fleſh; and fortify us with Strength to reſiſt Temptation, and excite us in earneſt to provide for <hi>Eternity.</hi> But how few will be perſwaded to admit ſuch Thoughts! Men like not to be jogg'd, to be awak'd; they are ready to quarrel with us, for diſturbing them; they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry we will not let them alone, to ſleep the ſleep of Death, till they awake in the Flames of <hi>Hell:</hi> And then with what an Accent of Sorrow, will it be ſaid? <hi>Lo!
<note place="margin">Pſal. lii. 7.</note> this is the Man, who made not God his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102130:40"/>Strength!</hi> Lo! <hi>this is the Man.</hi> This is the miſerable, deceiv'd Man, that was ſo wiſe in his own Eyes, ſo obſtinate in his own Way, who would not be advis'd, and he hath not now a Word to excuſe himſelf, nor a Friend to ſpeak for him, nor a drop of Water to quench his Thirſt, or cool his Tongue.</p>
            <p>I know very well, <hi>ſome Subjects</hi> may be helpt by choſen Words, by Figures of Rhetorick, and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Eloquence: But there are <hi>Others,</hi> too great for Words: And this is <hi>one, Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able State of Mankind in another World.</hi> The Thing it ſelf, the Change that Death will make, exceeds all our weak Idea's. No Human Language can expreſs the thouſandth part of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Matter: As when we ſpeak of the <hi>Bleſſed GOD,</hi> and his Perfections, his Love, or his Wrath; ſo of the Bleſſedneſs of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:102130:40"/>Saints; and the Intolerable Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Devils and Damned Spirits; the Subject is too big for our Scanty Words: We can find out none that will fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the thing
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Blackall, <hi>of the Sufficiency of Scripture Motives.</hi> 2d Sermon of Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Lecture for the Year 1700.</note>: For what Tongue can utter, or Heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the horrible State of ſuch a forlorn Creature? depriv'd at Death of all Earthly Comforts, and ſeparated for ever from the Joy and Glory, the Light and Comfort of God's Bleſſed Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the Felicity of the Saints; depriv'd of all Good that others enjoy, and he was once capable of; and never to ſee the Face of God, but fall under his Vengeance, without any Alloy of Comfort, or Hope to mitigate his Sufferings: Not only baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Heaven, but ſent accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:102130:41"/>into Everlaſting Fire, with the Devils. No wonder if there be horrible Lamentations, dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Cries and Screetches, deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Rage and Fury, when ſuch are made ſenſible of their Folly, and of their Miſery; ſenſible of what they have loſt, and of what they begin to ſuffer, and muſt for ever ſuffer without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion or End: All the Pains and Miſeries, and Torments, that any of Mankind, or all of them put together, in all Ages and Generations of the World, did ever endure here upon Earth, if all were join'd and united, for one Man to ſuffer, will be infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely leſs than the Puniſhment of every Impenitent Sinner after Death. Let us ſay all we can, and heap up <hi>Superlative</hi> upon <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative,</hi> we muſt ſpeak <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectively</hi> of the Miſery of loſt Souls. Let us enlarge our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Thoughts never ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102130:41"/>it, there's ſtill a great deal <hi>more</hi> and <hi>worſe,</hi> than we can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, or fear. The beſt Orator upon Earth, yea the higeſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel in Heaven cannot deſcribe it.</p>
            <p>What a diſmal Spectacle then is it, to ſee an Impenitent Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Creature, upon a Bed of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without any Concern about his Everlaſting State? gaſping for Breath, unable to live, ready to paſs into another World, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Guilt of all his Sins, and ſo under the Condemnation and Curſe of God? The Devils then wait for their Prey; what a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Portion muſt ſuch a Man have, before his Body be Buried, or put in a Coffin? He paſſes into another World, where is neither Wine, nor Women, nor Sports, nor Pleaſures, nor Friend, nor Comforter; but falls under the Wrath of God, Remedileſs, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable Wrath: when but a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102130:42"/>little before, it may be, he had Hopes of Heaven. And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of all the lamentable Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes that Humane Nature is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, there is none ſo terrible, as that of <hi>the Death of a Preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, Deceiv'd Sinner;</hi> who is confident of the Favour of God, that he is in the way to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſhall go to Heaven: For ſuch a One, one Moment after Death, to be ſeiz'd by the Devil, and carry'd into the place of Torment. Oh diſmal Thought! to have the Confidence of a whole Life broken in pieces in one Moment! How terrible to be found at Death, under the Wrath of God, when they would never believe it, nor conſider it, till too late! You can now Read or Hear a Sermon of <hi>an
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>See more of this.</hi> Serious Reflections on Time and Eternity. <hi>Sect.</hi> xix.</note> Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hell,</hi> and of the Miſery of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102130:42"/>a Loſt Soul, as one can bear a terrible Deſcription of a Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, who never was at Sea; but it will be quite another thing, if when you expect to be ſav'd, you drop into Hell.</p>
            <p>O look into the other World! make the Suppoſition of your own Death, and what is like to follow! Admit the ſerious Thoughts of it for a few Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Retire ſometimes on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for this. But with how few can we prevail for ſo much as this? You will not be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it, leſt it ſpoil your Mirth, damp your Pleaſure, make you Melancholly, and Sorrowful; but if you die in Sin, there will be nothing but Sorrow after Death. And in your preſent Caſe, I may ſay, <hi>As the Lord lives, and as thy Soul lives, there's but a Step between thee and Death;</hi> between thee and Intollerable, Endleſs Wrath. Now if you are
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:102130:43"/>a little awaken'd by a ſerious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Book, or Providence, and Conſcience begins to trouble you, and make you uneaſie, you have many things to divert and quiet it; but hereafter there will be nothing of all this. How little is this believed by ſuch as talk with a ſeeming Bravery, of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing violent Hands upon <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</hi> And in caſe of extream Pain, or any great Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to put an end to their own Lives, to <hi>diſpatch themſelves, and die by their own Hands.</hi> Is not this to proceed without the Leave of the great Governour of the World, whoſe Propriety they deſtroy, and againſt whoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence they Rebel, by ſuch an Act
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>That it is unlawful according to Natural Principles: See Mr.</hi> Adams's Eſſay <hi>concerning</hi> Self Murther. 8vo. <hi>newly printed.</hi>
               </note>? But if there be a <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell</hi> to follow Death, which the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102130:43"/>greateſt part of Mankind in all Ages, (at leaſt of all Chriſtians ten thouſand to one) have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, how hazardous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive is their Folly?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We may hence take our Meaſures of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> according to Mens Conduct and Care with reference to the other World, and <hi>the two Eternal States</hi> of Mankind. One would wonder how things of ſo great Moment ſhould be forgotten, and not alwaies in our Minds. Would it not be ſtrange
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Spurſtow. <hi>Medit.</hi> xliii. <hi>Upon Time and Eternity.</hi> 8vo.</note>, if a Man who was to be judg'd to morrow, and receive the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, either of a Cruel Death, or of a Rich and Honourable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, ſhould not keep in mind the Buſineſs of the next approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Day, without tying a ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102130:44"/>thread on his Finger, to mind him? Is it not ſtrange, that the Infinitely greater things, of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life or Death, ſhould not be remembred, and thought of, when we know not what a Day may bring forth? Will not the Folly be Inexcuſable, as well as the Puniſhment of Sinners Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, who ſhall feel Everlaſtingly, what they would not be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to fear. Suppoſe a Man, much deſirous of Sleep, and in his perfect Mind, ſhould have an Offer made, of one Nights ſweet Reſt, on condition to be puniſht an hundred years for it; would he accept of Sleep on ſuch terms? And do not they far worſe, and make a more fooliſh Choice, who for the ſhort Pleaſures of Sin, will loſe Eternal Life, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the enduring of Endleſs Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery! What is it that makes our Cares and Fears ſo Prepoſterous? That we are afraid of a little
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102130:44"/>Suffering here, and not of Hell? That we are Anxious about to morrow, and Thoughtleſs of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity? That we dread the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſlight the Thunderbolt?</p>
            <p>What Name can be given to that Folly, for a Man to own his Soul may be loſt for ever, and yet take no Care to ſave it? To believe an <hi>Everlaſting Heaven,</hi> and yet be at no Pains to obtain it? To own the Horror of <hi>God's Eternal Wrath</hi> for Impenitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and yet Live and Die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance? Theſe are Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies beyond common Madneſs, and of more Dangerous Conſequence. What will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of that Man's <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> who is not <hi>Wiſe</hi> enough to prevent Eternal Miſery? Who liv'd with ſome tolerable Reputation, as a Wiſe Man in this World; and yet ſo Dies, as to call himſelf <hi>Fool</hi> for ever, and ſuffer to all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity the Effects of his <hi>Folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:102130:45"/>
            <p>
               <q>Can the World, and all that I ſhall gain of it, ſave me from Wrath to come? Bring me off when I appear before the Barr of Chriſt? Prevent the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Condemnation? or Releaſe me from the Pit of Hell, if I am once ſent there? Or will it be any Refreſhment in the place of Torment, to think what a brave Figure I made on Earth? How many Hundreds a Year I had; How Large, and Beautifull, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and Convenient a Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; How much I was Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd; How many Servants to Attend me; How many Thouſand Pounds I got, ſpent, or laid up, or had the Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of: Will the Thoughts and Remembrance of theſe things give me any Comfort in Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Burnings? <hi>What's all this to me,</hi> if once my Soul be Loſt? Let us then judge Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:102130:45"/>Judgment, and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but conclude that is Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, and Beſt, which will prove ſo at Laſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Not <hi>to Believe</hi> the Eternal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell, after ſuch Clear Evidence, and Repeated Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Word of God, is egregious Folly: But not <hi>to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe</hi> them, and yet do nothing to eſcape, is more Aſtoniſhing. Who would drink a Draught of cooling Liquor, if told there is Poiſon in the Glaſs? And yet Men go on in Sin, and Drink in Iniquity like Water, though they are told the Wages of Sin is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death. All the Pleaſures of many Years in a courſe of Sin, cannot compenſate for a Man's Burning in a Furnace at the End of that time, though but for four and twenty hours: How is it then, that the repeated Threatnings of Everlaſting Deſtruction, ſhould not weigh more to keep us from
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102130:46"/>Sin, than the Gain of a little Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or the pleaſing a Friend, or gratifying an Appetite, in the ſhort Enjoyment of a forbidden Pleaſure? Who would chuſe to to be treated like a Prince, or a King, for one Day, or Week, or Month; if he knew he muſt at the end of that time be rackt and tortur'd to Death, and finiſh his Days in Exquiſite Torments? And what is this in Compariſon of Dying the <hi>Second Death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe that <hi>Origen</hi>'s Opinion ſhould be true,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jer. Taylor. <hi>The Fooliſh Exchangs,</hi> Serm. XIX.</note> That Curſed Souls ſhould have a Period to their Tortures, after <hi>a Thouſand Years,</hi> would it not be madneſs to chuſe the Pleaſure, or Wealth of a few Years now, (with Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Trouble, and Uncertainty,) and for this to endure the Flames of Hell for <hi>a Thouſand Years?</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:102130:46"/>When no Man hath Pleaſure for a Hundred Days together, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome intervening Trouble; or at leaſt a Wearineſs and Loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Pleaſure. A Thouſand Years is a long while to be in Torment. We find a Fever of one and twenty Days to be like an Age in length: But what's that to the Duration of an Into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable Miſery; <hi>for ever</hi> in the Height, and <hi>for ever</hi> Beginning? When ten thouſand Years ſhall have ſpent no part of its Term.</p>
            <p>The Compariſon of this Life with the other, of <hi>Time</hi> with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity,</hi> whether in Happineſs or Miſery, is of ſo much Moment, and Uſe; may ſerve to ſo many Excellent Purpoſes, and produce ſuch wiſe Thoughts and Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that I wiſh we would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the one and the other, more ſeriouſly and frequently: How little a while we are to abide here; and that after Death, we muſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102130:47"/>abide <hi>for ever</hi> in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, or in Torments; with God in Endleſs Glory, or in Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt Fire, with the Devil and his Angels.</p>
            <p>Oh think a little, how Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a thing is the longeſt Life of Man on Earth compar'd with <hi>an Everlaſting Duration!</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> xxxix. 5, 6. <hi>Thou haſt made my Days as an Hands breadth, and mine Age,</hi> (my Life, my little Time on Earth) <hi>is as nothing unto thee;</hi> compar'd with thy Duration, which is without <hi>Beginning</hi> or <hi>End.</hi> Old <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he had paſs'd one hundred and thirty Years, ſaith, <hi>Few and evil are the Days of the Years of the Life of my Pilgrimage.</hi> What was that to <hi>Adam</hi>'s nine hundred and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years, after his Creation in full Strength and Maturity? or to <hi>Methuſaleh</hi>'s nine hundred and ſixty Years? But what a Moment
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102130:47"/>is that to the Divine Eternity! <hi>A thouſand Years, in thy ſight, are but as one Day; or as Yeſterday when it is paſt,</hi> Pſal. xc. 5, 6. If it had been ſaid, ten thouſand millions of Years are but as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, it had been as true. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Computation, <hi>a Thouſand Years as one Day;</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Man had been born above <hi>five thouſand Years</hi> agoe, he is in God's ſight as one born <hi>five Days</hi> agoe. If the firſt Man were now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, he would not be <hi>ſix Days</hi> old, by that Reckoning. And by the ſame Account, he that hath liv'd in the World <hi>ſixty two Years</hi> hath liv'd but <hi>an Hour and half:</hi> And he that was born <hi>forty Years</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, is but as if he came into the World <hi>this preſent Hour. Yea, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as a Watch in the Night:</hi> A thouſand Years in God's ſight, is but as two or three Hours: And ſo <hi>threeſcore Years</hi> is but as <hi>five</hi> or <hi>ſix Minutes.</hi> But ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102130:48"/>millions of Years in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of GOD's ETERNITY, are leſs than one Unite, one Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute. How awful and uſeful may it be, to make the Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon between the longeſt Life; and Eternity?</p>
            <p>Upon the whole, who would not pray with <hi>David,</hi> that God would teach him to number his Days, and value his little Time, ſo as to apply his Heart to Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that he may walk <hi>in the way of Life, that is above to the Wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. xv. 24.</note> and <hi>depart from Hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> How unſpeakable a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard do they run, who delay their Repentance, eſpecially to the laſt Hour, to <hi>a Death-Bed?</hi> Have they any Aſſurance they ſhall not die <hi>ſuddenly;</hi> but be warned by Sickneſs? How many are diſpatch'd to the Grave and Hell, in the midſt of their Hopes
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102130:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>of living to Repent hereafter? The true reaſon of deferring it to hereafter, is not becauſe they intend to begin <hi>then,</hi> but becauſe they have no mind to begin <hi>now.</hi> And unleſs They be then in a better mind than at preſent, which by adding Sin to Sin is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, they will be for deferring it ſtill, even to their laſt Sickneſs. But do they know what kind of Sickneſs their laſt ſhall be? What if it be not a ſurprizing Apoplexy; yet in a ſtupid Lethargy; or a Raging Fever, they will have no Opportunity, or Leiſure to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent? And if they ſhould, they may not apprehend any Danger in their preſent Sickneſs, as if it would end in Death: Or they may not have the Grace (which they have ſo often forfeited,) to employ that time to ſo good a Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The common pretence, is the Example of the <hi>Thief on the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:102130:49"/>Croſs,</hi> that he upon a ſhort Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er found Mercy at laſt, and was promis'd an Admiſſion into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe that very Day: But think a little how extraordinary that Caſe was, as to <hi>the Time of it,</hi> when our Lord was Dying for Sinners; then to give ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Royalty of his Grace? The like Seaſon can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver happen again: And there is but <hi>this one Inſtance</hi> mention'd in the whole <hi>Bible.</hi> Beſides the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Proof which he gave of his Converſion, as to Repentance, Faith in Chriſt, Love to him, Charity to his Fellow-Sufferer, and the extraordinary Prayer which he made to Chriſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all manner of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, from what he ſaw, or heard at that time; makes his Caſe to be very different, from the ordinary Condition of Men upon a Sick-Bed.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:102130:49"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> As to any thing he ſaw: What was there as to outward Appearance, that repreſented Chriſt as the Son of God, and the King of Glory, while he ſuffered as a Criminal; hanging on a Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, or a Croſs, between two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors? (And in the midſt of them as the Chiefeſt of the three.) What Relation could this poor Man ſee between theſe Sufferings, this Ignominy, this wretched Death; between the Outrages, Reproaches, Scorns and Curſes which he endured, and his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Divinity, his Power and his Kingdom? And yet he owns him for his Saviour, tho' under the ſame Condemnation with himſelf. He ſees him nailed to the accurſed Tree; and yet prays to him, as if he were upon a Throne. He beholds him ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Cruel Death, and yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores him as Lord of Glory.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:102130:50"/>
            <p>Have we found ſuch Faith in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> or amongſt Chriſtians? even among thoſe of Chriſt's own Family, who have heard his Heavenly Doctrine and ſeen his Miracles; and had enjoyed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Converſe with him? Yet they forſook him, when he comes to be crucify'd. But here's a poor Penitent, who beholds him on the Rack, deſpiſed by his own Country-men, condemned by the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Men of Learning, Credit, and Authority; and Calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Reviled by a multitude of By-ſtanders: Yet owns Him for <hi>a King;</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> elſewhere; and ventures his Soul on his Power and Grace to make him Bleſſed after Death, tho' he ſaw him expire, and die in his view, and before his Eyes.</p>
            <p>O amazing Inſtance of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Faith! when there was ſo much to be ſeen at that Time to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:102130:50"/>diſcourage it. But neither the Face of Authority in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; nor the cry of the Common People for his Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion, nor the Scorn of the Chief Prieſts and Rulers, nor the Jeers of his Fellow-Sufferer, nor any the leaſt Jealouſie of his being unable to ſave him, could ſtop his Mouth: but by a moſt vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Act of Faith he pours out this Prayer with his laſt Breath, <hi>Lord, Remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us think a little, what could this poor Penitent behold, in our Dying Saviour, that ſhould make him believe, that his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him could avail him in another World? What was there in Appearance, for which he ſhould take him to be the Son of God, or ſo much as an Innocent Man? Was there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to an Eye of Sence, that did bear Teſtimony to the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:102130:51"/>and Excellency of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Could the Majeſty of his Countenance demand Reverence and Reſpect? was not his Face disfigured? What Royal Purple was there; but that of his own Blood, which trickled down from his Wounds? What Symptoms of his being Lord and <hi>King;</hi> that he ſhould think him to be ſuch in Reality, while the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> call'd him ſo in Scorn? What Crown had he on his Head, but one of Thorns; which was put on him as a mark of Infamy, and not as a Badge of Honour; not as a Royal Ornament, but as a Token of Reproach? In the Judgment of Sence, what Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures had he in his Hands to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of; when both his Hands were pierc'd, and faſtened to the Gibbit with Nails? If he be <hi>a King</hi> in the other World, where are the Cherubims and Seraphims, the Angels and the Heavenly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:102130:51"/>Hoſt, to make up his Retinue? If he be <hi>a King,</hi> where is his Crown and Scepter? his Guards and Train of Attendants; when his own Diſciples left him; and his Croſs was encompaſs'd with rude Soldiers, to prevent his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliver'd, if any ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it: And to render his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings the more publick and ſhameful; and yet by the Power of a Divine Faith, he cries out, <hi>Lord, remember me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Tho' he ſaw nothing that was Royal and Magnificent like a King, to encourage his Faith and Prayer, yet 'tis probable he might hear ſomething of that Nature: But if we reflect upon the Hiſtory of his Paſſion, we find no ſuch thing. What Words did he hear him ſpeak upon the Croſs, that might diſcover him to be the Meſſiah; or but an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſon? He heard him ſay, <hi>I
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:102130:52"/>thirſt;</hi> but was ſuch Weakneſs and Infirmity agreeable to one that was the Son of God? Could he be thought able to diſpoſe of the Kingdom of Heaven, that needed a little Water to quench his Thirſt? He heard him ſay, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> But could he judge him to be the beloved Son of God; and yet hear him thus complain, of his being forſaken? He heard him ſay, <hi>Behold my Mother:</hi> But how could he think that the King of Heaven, and Lord of Glory was born of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, his own Creature? What, in ſhort, did he hear, or ſee, that might encourage him to believe, that he was able to diſpoſe of the Heavenly Kingdom? And yet he deſires to be remembred by him as the Sovereign of it. What then can we think, or ſay as to his Caſe, but that he was taught of God, by the Holy Spirit, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:102130:52"/>into the Myſtery of the Croſs, as the way to the Crown; and perſwaded, that this was the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> who was to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with Tranſgreſſors, and wounded for Tranſgreſſions, and to make our Peace by his own Blood. His Senſes, you ſee, could not help his Faith in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let us further conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Excellency of his ſhort <hi>Prayer;</hi> and how different from the common <hi>Lord have mercy,</hi> of dying People after a wicked Life: <hi>Lord, remember me when thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into thy Kingdom.</hi> The Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Manner, and all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his Requeſt, are very Extraordinary. He does not beg to be deliver'd from his preſent Pain. He prays not to be ſav'd from that ſhamefull Death. He requeſts not to be taken down from the Croſs. That the Nails might be pluckt out of his Hands
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:102130:53"/>and Feet: Or that his ſenſe of Pain might be mortify'd; or his Sufferings ſhortned: That he might not feel his Torments at all; or but for a little while. No, he ſeems to have no Concern about the Sentence executed on him in this World; but begs that Chriſt would be kind to him in the next. <hi>Lord, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me, &amp;c.</hi> Is this the Voice of a Malefactor; or the Faith of a Diſciple? A ſtrange Requeſt, from ſuch a Perſon, at ſuch a Time; to our condemned, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, dying Lord! That a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, under the Sentence of Death, ſhould make ſuch an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to one that ſuffer'd as a Malefactor too! and venture his Eternal State on his Power to ſave him! By begging to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred of Chriſt in his Kingdom, he owns his Ability to ſave him; and that notwithſtanding the ſhamefull Circumſtances of his
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:102130:53"/>Humiliation, he was a Glorious King. Hereby he teſtifies his Hope, and Expectation of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Bleſſedneſs after Death; and in this Prayer profeſſeth his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of it, in the midſt of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in the midſt of Calumnies, in the proſpect of Death, before a vaſt Aſſembly of Scorners. He is not diſcourag'd, but ſpeaks it aloud before them all, not caring who heard him: <hi>Lord, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom.</hi> He was not ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd at his reproachfull Death. As if his Eye had been fixt on his Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, and Glory: And therefore talks of being remembred by him, as one who had Power to ſave him, and who was to be the Judge of quick and dead. <hi>Lord, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which way ſoever we view <hi>this Prayer,</hi> it is admirable, and aſtoniſhing. How weighty is the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:102130:54"/>Matter? How copious, full, and ſignificant the Senſe of every Word? And yet how humble and modeſt the Expreſſion? I ſay how <hi>modeſt</hi> the Expreſſion! <hi>Lord, remember me:</hi> i. e. Lord, I can preſume to crave nothing higher, nothing greater, nothing more of thee, than a <hi>bare Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi> O Lord, I beſeech thee remember me; and I leave it to thy Pleaſure to determin how, in what Manner, and to what Purpoſe, thou wilt remember me: He acknowledgeth the <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of Chriſt, as fitteſt to chuſe what Favour to grant him: with a Senſe at the ſame time of his own Unworthineſs of any; and owns the <hi>Mercy</hi> of Chriſt, as able to overlook that Unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that he had <hi>Power</hi> to grant and confer the Bleſſedneſs which he prays for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord, remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom,</hi> i. e.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:102130:54"/>Lord, Remember to receive my departing Soul: Remember to ſhew Pity to a dying Creature, that now, more than ever, needs it. <q>O Lord, I am paſſing into another World, my Joynts are ſtretched, my Heart pants, my Breath grows faint, I am even ready to dye: But my great Requeſt, my earneſt, my only Petition now is, that thou wouldeſt Remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom. Lord Jeſus, this is what I moſt humbly beg, that whither thou goeſt, I may go. That where thou ſhalt be, I may be. That I may have a Place with thee in Paradiſe. That I may be with thee in the other World <hi>in thy Kingdom.</hi> That then and there thou wouldeſt remember me; and be gracious to me, and mercifully receive my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Accept me now in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonies of Death; and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:102130:55"/>to acquit and own me af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Death, and let me dwell in thy bleſſed Preſence and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for ever.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Something of all this ſeems im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, and comprehended in his ſhort Prayer, <hi>Lord, remember me,</hi> &amp;c. Upon the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole, can any Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement be juſtly taken from this Example, for Men to delay their Repentance and Converſion to God till Old Age; or a Sick-Bed, and the Approaches of Death.</p>
            <p>As we have ſeen how extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary this Prayer was, we read how effectual it was alſo! How ſpeedily did he obtain a gracious Anſwer, for our Lord tells him, <hi>This Day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Nothing can match or parallel the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Grace of this Prayer, but the Kindneſs and Bounty of our Lord's Anſwer; <hi>This Day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> He
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:102130:55"/>craves a Remembrance of him, but our Lord promiſes him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent poſſeſſion: He begs a Favour, as of one that was Abſent, <hi>Lord, remember me,</hi> &amp;c. but Chriſt aſſures him, that he ſhall that very Day be preſent with him in the Happy Receptacle of Holy Souls depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>This Day ſhalt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There is no ground then from the Caſe of <hi>the Penitent Thief,</hi> for any man to count much upon future, dying Repentance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>His</hi> was Effectual, and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted at the laſt Hour.</p>
            <p>I grant, the Promiſes of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs are made to Repentance, to Confeſſion of Sin, and Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of forſaking it: But I fear it is not enough conſider'd. That what we read of this in the New Teſtament, doth eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<note n="*" place="bottom">Traité des Sources de la Corruption, <hi>qui regne aujour d'huy parmi les Chreſtiens,</hi> 8vo. Amſt. 1700. <hi>partie</hi> 1. §. 6. Le Renvoy de la Converſion.</note> 
               <hi>New Converts</hi> to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:102130:56"/>who were brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Chriſtian Faith, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd themſelves to be Baptized. Profeſſed Repentance was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of the Gentiles, on their firſt Entrance into the Chriſtian State; and therefore <hi>Repentance</hi> is mentioned amongſt the <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals,</hi> which the <hi>Catechumens</hi> were to be inſtructed in before, and in order to Baptiſm.
<note place="margin">Heb. vi. 1, 2.</note> With this they were to begin the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Life: But for Baptized Chriſtians, they are obliged to all holy Converſation and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And is there no hazard for Chriſtians to think to Finiſh where the Pagans were to begin? to think to enter into Heaven by the ſame Door, by which the Heathen entred into the viſible Church?</p>
            <p>I deny not <hi>the Poſſibility</hi> of a true and ſaving Repentance at laſt, for who can limit, or ſet bounds to the Free Grace of God;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:102130:56"/>but certainly <hi>a Death-bed Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is a very Deceitfull thing.</hi> Who can be aſſured that it is <hi>ſafe</hi> in it ſelf? or know that God doth accept Mens Repentance, and Sorrow for Sin, after a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Life, when they can Sin no more? That inſtead of a whole Life of Obedience to God, he will at laſt accept a few forced Tears and Prayers, with ſome fair Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Reſolutions to live well, when the Men are Sick, and muſt Die, and can live no longer, to ſin as formerly, if they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much a mind to it? 'Tis almoſt as reaſonable to
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Bates <hi>of Spiritual Perfection.</hi> Chap. XI.</note> expect that the Sun ſhould croſs the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Nature, and riſe in the Weſt, as that the Son of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhould ariſe with Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Wings upon an habitual obſtinate Sinner, at the laſt Hour.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:102130:57"/>
            <p>There needs an Extraordinary Grace, if their Repentance be true, to render it Comfortable to the Dying Penitent. For tho' we muſt follow a Judgment of Charity, yet God onely knows whether the Heart be changed, and whether the Life would be, if the Perſon Recovered. We have ſeen many ſeem Penitent and Devout upon a Sick Bed, who after they have been unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly reſtored to Health, have plainly proved their Repentance was not unto Life. I may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs this in the Words of a
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> Tillotſon <hi>on</hi> Eccleſ. viii. 11. <hi>Of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Long Suffering.</hi> Serm. VIII. Vol. VII.</note> Great Man. <q>Though Sincere Repentance at laſt be poſſible, it is almoſt impoſſible for the Party himſelf, much more for others, upon any good ground to judge when it is Sincere. God who knows the Hearts
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:102130:57"/>of all Men, only knows the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of it. I have therefore no great Opinion of that extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Comfort, which ſome have upon a ſudden Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for great Crimes, becauſe I cannot diſcern any ſufficient Ground for it. I think great Humility and Dejection of Mind, and a doubtful Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of their Condition, would much better become them; becauſe their Caſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo very doubtful in it ſelf: Let them exerciſe as deep Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance as poſſible, and bring forth all the Fruits meet for it, as are poſſible in ſo ſhort a time: And for the reſt, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly commit themſelves to the Mercy of God in Jeſus Chriſt. Let them imitate, as near as they can, the Behaviour of the <hi>Penitent Thief,</hi> the only Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Scriptures have left us of a late Repentance that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:102130:58"/>Effectual. He gave the greateſt Teſtimony of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; but we don't find in him any ſigns of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Comfort, much leſs of Confidence: But he humbly commended himſelf to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Goodneſs of his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſaying, <hi>Lord, remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This may primarily refer to the Caſe of Criminals, condemn'd to Death by the Civil Magiſtrate, but is applicable to any Man's ſudden Repentance upon a Sick-Bed, after a Wicked Life. It muſt needs be <hi>uncomfortable,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis ſo exceeding <hi>hazardous</hi> and <hi>doubtful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exhortation,</hi> under two Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Labour to be eſtabliſh'd in the Belief of theſe Truths; and to be ſuitably affected with
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:102130:58"/>them, <hi>viz.</hi> Theſe Important Truths of <hi>the two Eternal States.</hi> That we may ſoundly Believe, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider them. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon our Affections and Practice will be according to <hi>our Faith.</hi> Doubtleſs if we had ſuch a certain view, ſuch a clear Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the great things of the other World, as the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith may give us, it would break the Snare of moſt Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from Earthly things. If we did <hi>indeed</hi> believe the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Glory of <hi>Heaven;</hi> and the Intolerable Miſery of the Wicked in <hi>Hell;</hi> and the <hi>Eternity</hi> of both; as we believe, and are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the Truth of what we ſee, and feel, and know by our our Senſes. Let us then conſider, whether theſe things are true, or no; and apply them to our ſelves. Let us not apprehend the <hi>Diſtance</hi> to be very great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the preſent Pleaſures of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:102130:59"/>Sin; and the threatned Sufferings of another World; for how ſhort and uncertain a thing is the Life of Man? Let us not think it will be only the miſerable Portion of a <hi>few;</hi> when we have ſo much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think, that but <hi>very Few</hi> will be Eternally ſaved; in <hi>Compariſon</hi> of the many that will periſh. Let us not think in General, that this Miſery is only for ſuch, who are <hi>greater Sinners than we</hi> are. For if Hell were open to our view, we might ſee ſuch there, as once thought themſelves, in as fair a way for Heaven as we: And when they left the World, it was as little thought by their ſurviving Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, that they were Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as it would be ſuppoſed of us, if we ſhould now die.</p>
            <p>Let us not delude our ſelves by a Fooliſh Thought, as if the Judgment-Day was <hi>a great way off,</hi> and the Sufferings of the Wicked are not to be compleat
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:102130:59"/>till after that: For when the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked die, they are deprived of all they lov'd, for ever ſeparated from the Objects of their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and awaken'd to review their Sins, and underſtand their Folly. They Remember the Grace and Glory they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed; the Happineſs they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rejected; and all the Means and Helps they once had to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape Damnation. And ſo their own Conſcience muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, condemn, and reproach, for their Wilfulneſs, and Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy: That they were warned to flee from the Wrath to come, and they were offered Heaven, and Eternal Life: That they were urg'd again and again, not to loſe their Seaſon of Mercy, and Day of Grace: <hi>That they were entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> in time, to conſider the things that belong to their Eternal Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And muſt they not then ſuffer terrible things in the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:102130:60"/>State of Separation, under the Laſh of a Condemning, Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Mind, without any Hope of eſcaping the Tribunal of their Judge, or of avoiding, or defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Execution of his terrible Sentence? How dreadful muſt it be, to loſe the Favour of God for ever, and lie in Torment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Wrath, with the weight of this killing Thought; <q>That this is the Effect of my own Madneſs; the Fruit of my own Choice; 'tis a Rod of my own making; 'tis Miſery of my own procuring: I have undone, and deſtroy'd my ſelf?</q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſome will be able to ſay further: <q>I was convinc'd of Sin, and reſolv'd to turn from it. I had many Struglings of Conſcience, and many Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things of the Divine Spirit: I did begin to ſeek after God: I was almoſt perſwaded; there was a time, when I was not
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:102130:60"/>far from the Kingdom of God: But I return'd again to Folly, and harden'd my Heart. I had Knowledge, I had Time, I might have had Aſſiſtance and Helps, of many ſorts: I had repeated Warnings; I was faithfully admoniſhed; and for ſome time I profeſs'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; I confeſs'd Sin; I wept for Sin, I pray'd againſt it: I went ſo far as to own my Baptiſm, and enter into So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn <hi>Covenant</hi> with God; and renew it at his Table: But I lov'd my Sins and Luſts, and quickly broke all theſe Bonds, and harken'd to my old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions and Acquaintance, and was worſe afterward than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let us think often with our ſelves, How certain is the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs of the Saints? How inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and intolerable the Miſery of Sinners, on whom the Wrath
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:102130:61"/>of God ſhall abide? Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd with the fooliſh talk of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, who are undone for ever, if the Holy Scriptures be the Word of God; I ſay, <hi>for ever,</hi> (as hath been prov'd from the Old and New Teſtament) without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe, or Period. <hi>Abraham</hi> did not go about to comfort the Rich Man in Hell with any ſuch falſe Stories; That after he had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd a while, he ſhould be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leas'd: But tells him, <hi>the Gulf was fix'd.</hi> This will be the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Accent of their Sufferings, to have no Hope of End; but after having ſuffer'd as many Millions of Ages, as there are Sands on the Sea-ſhore ten thouſand times told; yet an <hi>Eternity</hi> of Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings is ſtill to come: After ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving endured Torment, for as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Millions of Years and Ages, as there be drops of Water in the Ocean, yet not one Moment nearer the End of their Torments.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:102130:61"/>The Continuance of their Miſery ſhall not be meaſur'd by Time; but by the Immutability of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice, and the boundleſs Abyſs of Eternity.
<note place="margin">Rev. ii. 11. Rev. xxi. 8.</note> 'Tis <hi>the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death,</hi> (not the turning our Souls and Bodies into nothing,) but ſuch a Death, by which they may <hi>be hurt.</hi> They that die that Death ſhall be hurt by it, which could not be, if they were to be Annihilated: <hi>A Lake burning with Fire and Brimſtone, is the ſecond Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Death without the Power of Dying; and yet with the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Deſire of it, whoſe Sting can never be taken out. whoſe Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror is as Everlaſting, as the Joys of Heaven. There's nothing of Life remaining in this Death; but the Senſe of Miſery, and the Knowledge of that to be Endleſs. And that this Dark Night ſhall never be ſucceeded by the Light of any Morning. They ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:102130:62"/>live, to be ever miſerable; to feel Torments unto Infinite Ages, to a boundleſs and never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ending Eternity. They ſhall wiſh, and endeavour not to be; and yet ſubſiſt, and not die. Always ſuffer without ever ceaſing to live and ſuffer.
<note place="margin">Rev. ix. 6.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall ſeek Death but not find it; Death ſhall flee from them.</hi> They ſhall never be able to ſay, <hi>the Bitterneſs of Death is paſt:</hi> It will be Wrath to come after numberleſs Ages. Theſe are <hi>terrible things</hi> to hear of, but how much more to experience. What Heart can endure theſe Thoughts, without Fear and Trembling? Who for the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Sin for a ſeaſon, would hazard the enduring this endleſs Wrath? Better to ſuffer all the Pains and Miſeries we are capable of in this World, for a thouſand Years; than the Pains of Hell for one Hour. But to endure them <hi>for ever;</hi> without Hope of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:102130:62"/>End! this ſinks the Soul under Anguiſh and Deſpair, that none of our Words or Thoughts can reach.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>Eternity! Eternity!</hi> Is it true, or can it poſſibly be falſe, after ſo many expreſs Scriptures to aſſert it? that there will be no Period to the Miſery of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: That the Fire ſhall burn to all Eternity: That the Worm of Conſcience ſhall gnaw for ever: The Truth of this would ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it an unſpeakable Favour, to be releas'd after a Hundred or a Thouſand Years; after a Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ten thouſand Millions of Years and Ages. To have any Hope of an End 'twould be ſome ſupport: But this word <hi>Never, Never</hi> End, will make the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Rage, and Roar with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh: There is not ſo much as a Poſſibility of Deliverance to faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en their Hope upon. 'Tis <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Deſtruction:</hi> The Gulf will
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:102130:63"/>be fix'd; the Bridge will be drawn; the Door will be ſhut; every Anchor of Hope broken: 'Tis <hi>for ever;</hi> it is to all <hi>Eternity.</hi> Oh think of it, as not more <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible</hi> than <hi>Certain!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh that I could perſwade you, to Believe, and Apply theſe things to your ſelves. That under the Profeſſion of Religion, with ſo much Light and Knowledge, you may not be undone, by <hi>Inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</hi> For if we would but think a little, what Eternity is; and conſider the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Heaven and Hell, it muſt needs have ſome Effect. If there were only <hi>a Poſſibility</hi> of the Truth of things ſo vaſtly Great and Important, (tho' we had no certain Revelation,) it ſhould be enough to deter us from Sin, and awaken us to utmoſt Diligence to prepare for another World. He is not reckoned a Wiſe Man for the World, who lays up no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:102130:63"/>againſt Old Age when it is in his Power, tho' it's <hi>poſſible</hi> he may not live to be Old: But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch Aſſurance of Eternal Life; and the Bleſſedneſs of the one State, and the Miſery of the other, being ſo unſpeakably great; how ſhould our Minds and Hearts be intent upon what relates to that World, more than upon the Affairs of this? Oh beg of God to ſtrengthen your Faith, and fix the Conſideration of theſe things on your Minds and Hearts. One would wonder that Men can ſleep, and wake, lie down, and riſe, and go from Week to Week about the Affairs of their Calling, and the Buſineſs of the World, as if there were no Truth in any thing of all this; or no Danger of their loſing Heaven, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling under the Sentence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation! What can we ſay to it, that profeſſing to believe a <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> we yet live as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:102130:64"/>if we were certain there was <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> We walk with the ſame Security, Peace, and Joy, in the way to <hi>Hell,</hi> as if we were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that all that is ſaid of it were only a Romantick Story. We loſe the Kingdom of God with as much Indifference, as if we believ'd nothing of it. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the very Name of <hi>Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> with Men of any Faith, or Reaſon, ſhould blaſt all the Beauty and Glory of this World; and weaken the Force of the moſt Powerful Temptations. Methinks one Thought of <hi>Eternity</hi> ſhould awaken, quicken, and make us ſerious, when we are moſt cold, dull, or ſleepy. To be for <hi>ever, ever, ever</hi> with the Lord in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or under his moſt heavy Wrath: What Words are theſe! what Things? what Thoughts are theſe! Shall I not reflect, and enquire, which of the <hi>two</hi> is like to be <hi>my Portion?</hi> What if I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:102130:64"/>ſhould die ſuddenly, in the State I am now in, will my Immortal Soul be loſt or ſav'd? Am I a Stranger to Faith and Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unreconcil'd to God, in a ſtate of Damning Ignorance and Unbelief? or what Evidence can I give of <hi>Repentance towards</hi> God, and <hi>Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Bleſſedneſs of <hi>Heaven</hi> will not draw me, let me ſometimes try the Thoughts of <hi>Hell</hi> to awaken my drowſie Sowl: Let me not fear to make uſe of that Motive, to work upon my Fear;
<note place="margin">Heb. xii. 29.</note> even <hi>our God is a Conſuming Fire.</hi> Some weak and deceiv'd People ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it legal, and below the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality of a Chriſtian, to preach, or think much of <hi>the Damnation of Hell:</hi> But they conſider not, that the Puniſhment of Sinners in onother World, is oftner threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd, and more largely deſcrib'd in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> than in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:102130:65"/>the <hi>Old.</hi> Our Saviour has ſaid <hi>more,</hi> of an Everlaſting Hell, than all the Prophets: And therefore to diſlike, or condemn this Help, to work upon our Fears; is in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect to make themſelves wiſer than GOD, more Evangelical than <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and more Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual than St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>But the moſt are loth to apply ſuch Thoughts for another Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for fear of the Sentence their own Conſcience will paſs upon them now, rather than of the Condemnation that God will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict hereafter. Such Truths, if admitted to be certain, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd to a Man's particular Caſe, who lives in Sin, would diſturb his Peace, and damp his Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; would chill, and cool his Carnal Mirth; would check his purſuit after fleſhly Luſts, and turn his fooliſh Jollity into Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Darkneſs. He can't
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:102130:65"/>think of ſuch things, without a ſad miſgiving Heart. Even they that ſeem to deſpiſe, and deny all this, yet owe all their Peace to their <hi>not thinking</hi> of it. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their falſe Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in Company, they tremble when alone. If they dare think of Death, and another World in the Darkneſs of the Night; they find by their own Thoughts, that the Candle of the Lord within them is not extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us follow the Counſel of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>his Apoſtles;</hi> I mean, let us hearken to the Word of God in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, if we would not come into this place of Torment, but have our Portion in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom. This I gather from the Cloſe of this Parable. The Believing Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the two Eternal States would engage us to this. It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:102130:66"/>methinks in the Deſire of the Rich Man in Torment, to prevent his Brethren's falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the like Ruin; (by his ſending one into the other World to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them,) that the not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or conſidering a future State was that which was like to undoe them. They did not live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not believe or conſider the other World. He thought there was ſo much ſtrength in this Argument of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> to bring Men to Repentance; that he did not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but it would prevail on his Wicked Brethren: If one went from the Dead, and told them what he ſuffered; and what would be their ſad Condition hereafter, if they did not now prevent it. Doubtleſs he thought as to himſelf, that if he had been permitted to live again, he ſhould have been another Man, and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:102130:66"/>liv'd another ſort of Life; and ſo concluded, that they would alſo, if they did but believe the two Eternal States; and that if one came from the Dead, they would believe it.</p>
            <p>We have commonly the ſame kind of Thoughts, that ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary means would prove effectual: But <hi>Abaham</hi>'s final An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Rich Man's Requeſt, tells us our miſtake; that <hi>if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not Moſes and the Prophets, neither ſhould we be perſwaded, tho' one came from the Dead.</hi> The Ordinary means, by the Word are ſufficient for our Conviction; and they that will not by them be perſwaded, do <hi>unreaſonably,</hi> and in <hi>vain</hi> deſire Extraordinary. I ſay unreaſonably, for it would deſtroy the End and Efficacy of Miracles, by the two great fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency of them; and make God's Almighty Power to become Cheap, if at every turn, it were
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:102130:67"/>to be thus employ'd, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of every man's Doubts and Scruples. There is almoſt the ſame Reaſon, why Miracles ſhould not be ſo common; as there is, why there ſhould be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at all. And it may be we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves in thinking we ſhould be <hi>certainly</hi> perſwaded, by ſuch a Miracle. If One might come from Heaven with the Light and Glory of the Lord ſhining in his Face, and ſpeak of the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Honours, and Felicity of the Saints above: We think that then we ſhould believe what is ſaid of <hi>Heaven.</hi> Or if One of thoſe miſerable Creatures that are paſt Hope, ſhould appear in ſome frightful Shape, Roaring and Yelling under the Wrath of God, with deſpairing Cries and Scree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſhould tell us with his Flaming Tongue and Breath; what is the ſad Portion of thoſe that know not God, and obey
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:102130:67"/>not the Goſpel; we conclude, we ſhould then no longer doubt of Hell, or continue to live as if we disbeliev'd it. But we are here told, that the Teſtimony of God in the Holy Scriptures is à more certain Evidence than that can be. If ſuch a One ſhould come from the Dead, what could he tell us of Heaven and Hell, more than has been told us already by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>the Prophets,</hi> by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>his Apoſtles?</hi> Can there be greater Arguments made uſe of to bring Men to Repentance, than are in the Holy Scriptures? Can we hear of a better Heaven, or a hotter Hell than is deſcribed in the Word of God? Or may we hope for the Concurrence of God's Grace with that, rather than with his Word? Such an Apparition may affect our Senſes, and ſtrike our Minds a little for the preſent; but would not turn the Will, nor change the Heart,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:102130:68"/>nor reform the Life. We ſee that by the Caſe of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who had ſeveral Miraculous Plagues, one would think enough to convince him, but he harden'd his Heart ſtill. We ſee it in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who notwithſtanding the ſight of continu'd Miracles for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years, they are complain'd of as a Stiffneck'd,
<note place="margin">Pſ. lxxviii. 22, 23, 24.</note> &amp; Rebellious People. Yea our Lord himſelf roſe from the Dead, and his Reſurrection was confirm'd by Five Hundred Witneſſes, and yet how few Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd it? We cannot have ſuch Certainty of a particular Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as of the Reſurrection of Chriſt. And you'd find it hard to diſtinguiſh a true Miracle in that caſe from a Counterfeit. How many in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are deceived by Stories from the Dead? If you had your Deſire granted in this, would you not be tempted to take it for a Spectre, a Phantom, a waking
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:102130:68"/>Dream, a melancholy Mormo? But if you ſhould believe it, and it ſhould affright you for a little while, yet 'tis very probable that the Impreſſion would by degrees wear off. As we find by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Perſons from the Brink of the Grave, who apprehended themſelves in the very terrour of Death, and the Pains of Hell did almoſt compaſs them about, they were then full of Sorrow for Sin, made many Reſolutions againſt it; but we find upon reſtored Health, it quickly comes to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, they relapſe into their old Sins, and are not perſwaded, even by their own Convictions.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Lazarus</hi> had been ſent to the Rich Man's Brethren, was it likely they would have Believed him? Might they not have plauſibly rejected the Meſſage, and ſuppos'd it to be a Cheat? How could they imagin that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> would take ſuch a one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:102130:69"/>his Boſom, as <hi>poor Lazarus;</hi> or employ him on ſuch an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand? 'Twould have been a Diſgrace to their Family, to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſuch a Report of their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Damnation; eſpecially when brought by ſuch a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. It may be they would no more have hearken'd to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> now teſtifying from the other World, than heretofore when begging at their Brother's Door. The Luſts and Vices of Men would very likely hinder the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of ſuch a Miracle as this, and find ways and ſhifts to evade the Force of it, as well as reſiſt the Evidence and Force of what is laid down in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>What is ſaid here in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to be denied to <hi>One Lazarus,</hi> was granted as to <hi>Another;</hi> that is, our Lord did raiſe one of that Name from the Dead, after he had been Dead four Days, and yet ſome of them who knew him
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:102130:69"/>before, and when he was Dead, and Riſen again, and convers'd with him afterwards, yet were not convinced by that Miracle of Chriſt, to Believe on him: for we read,
<note place="margin">Joh. xi. 53.</note> That from that very Day of raiſing <hi>Lazarus, The High Prieſts and Rulers took Counſel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, how they might put him to Death.</hi> And we read of One, <hi>blind</hi> and <hi>dumb,</hi> and <hi>poſſeſſed of a Devil,</hi> who was healed by Chriſt, <hi>Matth. XII.</hi> 22. (where were three Miracles in one,) and yet it did not convince, for we read, <hi>ver.</hi> 38. <hi>Certain of the Scribes and Phariſees ſay unto him, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter we would ſee a Sign.</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our Lord had miraculouſly fed Five Thouſand Perſons, with Five Loaves and Two Fiſhes, <hi>Joh. VI.</hi> ſome of thoſe very Men who had ſeen the Miracle, and eaten of it, and were ſo far convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for the preſent, as to ſay to one another, <hi>This is of a Truth the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:102130:70"/>Prophet, that ſhould come into the World.</hi> Yet the next Day, or within a Day or two, when he told them, they followed him for the Loaves, <hi>They ſay unto him, What Sign ſheweſt thou, that we may See, and Believe;</hi> as if he had never wrought a Miracle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Yea the Diſciples of Chriſt himſelf, who were Witneſſes of ſo many Miracles, were not ſo far perſwaded by them, as not to forſake him, nay not to deny him.</p>
            <p>To Conclude, We are not to expect any ſuch Extraordinary Method for our Conviction, while the ſtanding Revelation of the Will of God in the Scriptures is ſufficient; and the Doctrin there taught hath been abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by Miracles. And if one ſhould riſe from the Dead, and appear to us, 'tis probable enough it would not perſwade us to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, if the Word of God will not perſwade us. But <hi>no other
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:102130:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>Sign,</hi> our Lord ſays, <hi>ſhall be given, but that of Jonas the Prophet.</hi> That is, what's ſignified by it, <hi>the Reſurrection of Chriſt.</hi> And that hath been Confirm'd by numerous and undeniable Miracles, by all manner of Evidence and Proof, that ſuch a matter of Fact is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of. Which will leave us without Excuſe, if we Believe not his Doctrine; the Truth of which is ſealed by his Riſing from the Dead. We ſhould therefore ſtudy the Holy Scriptures, and the Rational Grounds of our Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſt to be the Son of God; and conſequently that All that he hath told us of the Other World, will moſt infallibly come to paſs. <hi>His Reſurrection</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the Truth of all. And we are not to expect Any more to Riſe from the Dead, till We our Selves do, unto our Laſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Book is ſeal'd, as the Gulf too is fixt: And they that
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:102130:71"/>hear not <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> are not like to be perſwaded at all. But if <hi>the Goſpel continues to be hid,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. iv. 3.</note> it is hid to them who are Loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS to our Deceas'd Friend, Mr. <hi>Shatterden Thomas,</hi> whoſe <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd this Diſcourſe, and at whoſe <hi>Deſire</hi> I preach'd, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it; what I ſhall ſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him from my Self, ſhall be more in the General, becauſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Particulars, I apprehend will be mention'd with more Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, from the Account given of him by a very Worthy and fit Perſon, who frequently viſited him in his laſt Sickneſs; whoſe Acquaintance with him, Love to the Memory of his good Mother, Reſpect for his Family and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and tender Compaſſion to his Caſe, made her willing to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:102130:71"/>diſcourſe him, and give that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Counſel and Advice, which oftentimes is better and more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually receiv'd from ſuch a Friend, than from a Miniſter. And his juſt Regard for her Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Character, made him likely to be Impreſſed by what ſhe ſaid to him. I hope it may have the like good effect upon Others, to recite a part of what ſhe had wrote down, tho' at firſt only for her own Satisfaction, and the good of her Children.</p>
            <p>I am glad I have leave to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn that Paper, becauſe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many of the ſame things I mention'd to him, are there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, and enlarg'd with his more diſtinct and particular An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers: But ſeveral will more can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly receive, and regard the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of ſuch Paſſages, from the Mouth of a dying Penitent, when confirm'd by ſuch a Teſtimony, than they would from my ſingle
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:102130:72"/>Report. I know the Scepticiſm of many of our Age is ſuch, as to reckon that a Miniſter ſpeaking on ſuch a Subject, doth it but <hi>in Form,</hi> according to his Profeſſion; and that it is an Art to carry on, what they call, his Trade. But all ſuch Cavils, Prejudices, and Objections will be hereby prevented, when I give you the Relation of what paſs'd, between him and that Pious La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as plainly and faithfully ſet down by her own Pen, and in her own Words, without alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any of the Phraſes; which as they need not to be alter'd, ſo to attempt it, would be to weaken the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Beauty,</hi> and the <hi>Pungency</hi> of the Diſcourſe of a Serious Chriſtian, with a Dying Friend.</p>
            <p>But before the Recital of that Paper, I have Some things to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part which I obſerv'd my ſelf, and Some which he deſired me
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:102130:72"/>to mention. And if I ſhould here uſe the greateſt <hi>Freedom,</hi> as to Particulars, I had not only Leave, but <hi>Order,</hi> (as ſeveral can witneſs,) not only Liberty and Allowance, but a <hi>Charge,</hi> often repeated to me, by our Deceaſed Friend, <hi>Not to ſpare him, Not to ſpare him;</hi> in Hope, that tho' he had not honour'd God by his Life, He might by his Sickneſs, and Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Repentance</hi> appear'd to be ſo unfeigned and ſincere, that he matter'd not if his own Name did ſuffer, ſo he might but Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, and Vindicate Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by any thing I could ſay of him, that had a Tendency to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the Living. But I ſhall not need, for that end, to mention any more of his Faults than is requiſite to illuſtrate his <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> and render me Faithful in the Charge I receiv'd. I ſhall touch that part with more Soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:102130:73"/>than he deſir'd, or than I am ſure he himſelf did, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing his Deteſtation of his paſt Life. I have too much Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion for his ſurviving Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, (who may profit by the Example of his Repentance, and I heartily beg they may,) than to ſay any thing that may obſtruct it, by Shocking and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking them. The very Parable whereof the Text is a part, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids me to act otherwiſe: for our Saviour conceals the Name of <hi>the Rich Man,</hi> whoſe Character is repreſented with ſuch Severity: And <hi>Abraham</hi> calls him <hi>Son,</hi> tho' a loſt and undone Wretch, whom he could not help, either to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe from his Torments, or procure the leaſt mitigation of them.</p>
            <p>I hope they who knew Him, eſpecially who were often in his Company, will remember the profeſs'd Change of his Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:102130:73"/>and the ſerious Counſel he gave to <hi>Several of them.</hi> God grant they may make ſuch juſt Reflections, Application, and Improvement of what he ſaid, as he deſir'd. And a Dying Man's Advice may by ſome be more minded, than any thing they hear from the Pulpit. He gave that Reaſon why he would have me print, becauſe ſome of <hi>his Companions,</hi> who would not hear what I ſhould Preach, he hop'd, would read what was Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his Repentance; and take Warning. He choſe to take that way to ſpeak to them <hi>All;</hi> but diſcovered a very particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for <hi>Some</hi> of them, who he thought might have been the worſe for his Company.</p>
            <p>After many Advantages, by his Parentage and Education, for the Knowledge and Practice of Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Religion, (which were not improv'd to the beſt Purpoſes)
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:102130:74"/>He was for ſome time ſunk ſo far into a Careleſs Neglect of it, as made him more eaſily be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by theſe Temptations, to which Perſons of his Age and Circumſtances are commonly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd. But God was Merciful, not to cut him off in that unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py State, and at laſt to favour him with a lingering Sickneſs of ſeveral Months, which gave him Time, and a Call to Repent. And during all that Space, wherein he gradually declin'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd, he had his Mind clear, and his Thoughts free, with little or no Bodily Pain, to diſcompoſe him: So that the Change of his Opinion and Judgment of things, and what he ſaid in the Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Repentance, was not the effect of Vapours, or a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd Head. But he had Death and the Grave ſo long in view be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, as gave him a favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Opportunity, as well as
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:102130:74"/>Warning to prepare for <hi>the Other World;</hi> which, tho' he never disbeliev'd, yet he had liv'd too much without any ſerious Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Concern about it.</p>
            <p>He was very well pleas'd, and very thankful to God, that <hi>ſeven or eight Weeks</hi> before he dy'd, his Phyſicians adviſed him to change the Air, and come from <hi>Highgate</hi> to <hi>London:</hi> This he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently comply'd with, having his Mind more awakened than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, to prepare for his great Change, and glad to be aſſiſted in ſo important a Work; for which he hoped he might <hi>here</hi> have more Advantage and Help. I had wrote to him with Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and Affection ſome Days before this, which I found was well receiv'd; and he heartily thank'd me for it, upon his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Town; tho' he had not Strength, he told me, to read much of the Book I recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:102130:75"/>as ſuitable to his Caſe. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he acknowledged, that it was owing to that Letter, that he came to die at <hi>London:</hi> And before that, it had put him upon Secret Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which before he had too much neglected. And it made way for his uſing me with leſs Reſerve, than any other Relation, and to ſpeak his Mind to me with more Freedom, than to any other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter who attended him.</p>
            <p>Before he came to <hi>London,</hi> and was brought ſo very low, apt Endeavours had been uſed to faſten upon him ſome more ſenſe of his Danger, and more ſerious Thoughts of another World, than he ſeem'd to diſcover. But till God by <hi>his Grace</hi> was pleas'd to awaken him, and ſoften his Heart, they ſeem'd to have little effect. The <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of that <hi>Grace</hi> he often acknowledg'd, in his laſt Sickneſs. When I told him that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:102130:75"/>was exalted as a Prince and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to give <hi>Repentance</hi> as well as <hi>Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> and that he muſt ſeek to him for Grace to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, as well as for Pardon: He ſaid, he knew very well that a good Education alone would not doe; nor Sickneſs, without the Effectual Grace of God, to change the Heart of an habitual Sinner, who was accuſtomed to doe Evil: And that this Grace was not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily to be expected <hi>at laſt,</hi> by thoſe who neglected God in their Health, and did not ſeek after him, till they came to dye. I encourag'd him to hope for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and told him, <hi>We are ſaved by Hope,</hi> and without it, we muſt periſh. I diſcourſed to him of the Riches, Freeneſs, and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of God's Grace, and the General Call and Invitation of the Goſpel. I minded him of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Penitent Malefactor, who was Crucify'd with Chriſt,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:102130:76"/>and his Effectual Prayer at laſt. <hi>Lord, Remember me when thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into thy Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. He did not yield to the Temptation to <hi>Deſpair,</hi> though he had a juſt, and great Remorſe for his paſt Offences againſt God; for his Neglect and Contempt of him, and for Sins of Omiſſion, aggravated by his Education, and Knowledge of the Principles of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whereof he had a great ſhare. And which is the more to be pity'd, he had withall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Natural Parts; ſo that if he had apply'd himſelf to Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and Diligently endeavour'd to Cultivate and Improve his Mind, he might have liv'd to have been very Serviceable in the World. This he himſelf reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on, and mentiond with Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p>When I told him I was the more encouraged to aſſiſt him and pray for him in his laſt Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:102130:76"/>becauſe of <hi>his Parentage and Family,</hi> as deſcending from good Parents, who had devoted him to God, and often pray'd for him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He anſwer'd, that in ſome Reſpects it was an Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement; but, ſaith he, it is the aggravation of my Folly and Sin, that after ſuch Advantages, I have liv'd no better.</p>
            <p>Under ſuch Apprehenſions of himſelf, and his nearneſs to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, you'll eaſily believe that he ſpent much of his Time in <hi>Prayer.</hi> His Heart was lifted up to God continually Day and Night, when others thought he was Aſleep, and ſometimes when they thought he was talking to himſelf.</p>
            <p>He diſcover'd a great Value for <hi>the Holy Bible,</hi> and Recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Reading and Studying of it, above any other Books of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; which are all, but to help us to underſtand, and improve
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:102130:77"/>
               <hi>that,</hi> and to imprint upon our Minds and Hearts, the Truths con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in the Holy Scriptures. He frequently lamented the Caſe of ſuch, as were <hi>Ignorant of the Principles of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> ſaying, what can be done for them, upon a Sick Bed, when there is no Foundation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Knowledge? <q>A good Education in the Knowledge of the Principles of Chriſtianity, he ſaid, might be of Uſe, one time or other. It will help to preſerve us from ſome Sins, (as I know by Experience) and we cannot ſo eaſily, or ſo ſoon fall into others, and may very much aſſiſt our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance afterward. And though the Advantage of it do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently appear, it may be of uſe, even in the laſt Scene of a Man's Life.</q> As was very Evident in his own Caſe.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:102130:77"/>
            <p>He ſpake often of the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Good Man's Condition, who lives a Regular, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable Life, and hath Hope in God, through Jeſus Chriſt, for another World; and the vaſt Difference between the Caſe of ſuch, and of thoſe who live in Sin, and have no well-grounded Peace; eſpecially after a good Education, and againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Theſe, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> have commonly a very uneaſy time of it, by reaſon of the Checks and Challenges of their own <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> He ſadly owned, that of late Months, he had had many Uneaſy and Reſtleſs Nights; for <hi>he had often gone againſt his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to divert it.</hi> And thought the Diſturbance of his Mind had been a great hindrance of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. He profeſt that he had more Peace and Comfort <hi>now,</hi> in his Repentance and ſeeking after God, and could ſleep better,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:102130:78"/>(tho' he was not certain what God would do with him,) than for ſix Months paſt: He loathed his paſt Life, ſaying, <hi>He would rather die than live ſo again:</hi> And was the leſs deſirous to live, leſt he ſhould again fall by Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, tho' as far as he knew his own Heart, he ſhould deteſt and abhor to do ſo; for he had now, other Thoughts of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, of the Lord's-Day, of Sin, and of the World, of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, of Preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than formerly.</p>
            <p>God had mercifully kept him from ſome ſorts of <hi>Youthful Luſts,</hi> by which many others have been defiled, inſnared, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. He could not be charged with Lewdneſs and Debauchery, as to <hi>Women;</hi> altho' by Bodily Temper and Conſtitution, he was leſs inclin'd to that Sin, yet <hi>Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Drinking, he ſaid,</hi> doth ſo commonly introduce, and make
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:102130:78"/>way for Uncleanneſs; (Theſe Sins are ſo ſeldom ſeparated,) that it was not owing to himſelf, but to the Providence, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining Grace of God. He did not therefore go about to excuſe himſelf, but acknowledged his own Vileneſs. <q>Tho' ſome, he ſaid, will be ready to leſſen my Faults, and ſay of me, that I have not liv'd ſo ill as many Others: I have not been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch notorious Crimes, as ſeveral Young Men; <hi>Only Drinking:</hi> But this is one of the greateſt Sins, becauſe it leads to all Other; and many Others are involv'd in it. I have neglected God, and liv'd as without him in the World, and tho' I did not Swear, Curſe, and Blaſpheme, yet I did not Worſhip, and Obey God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As to <hi>Exceſs in Drinking,</hi> He ſaid, 'twas <hi>Idleneſs</hi> and <hi>Company</hi> led him to it; adding, that the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:102130:79"/>want of an Employment lays a Man open to all Temptations. His good Temper and Diſpoſition, made him leſs able to reſiſt that of <hi>Company.</hi> He directed me thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to warn Others againſt it, in his Funeral Sermon. Particularly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>that Curſed Practice</hi> (I uſe his own words) <hi>That Curſed Practice,</hi> of going to a Tavern on the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> and order'd me to recommend <hi>the ſtrict Obſervation of the CHRISTIAN SABBATH,</hi> the Neglect, or Profanation whereof, makes way for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wickedneſs; and provokes God to leave Men to the Power of Temptation. Let Men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend what they will, <hi>he ſaid,</hi> if they have no regard to the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> I am ſure their Religion is vain.</p>
            <p>This I hope will be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, is none of the Peculiar Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents of <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> but the receiv'd Doctrine of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:102130:79"/>Church:
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Homilies of the Church of</hi> E. <hi>Hom.</hi> xx. Of the Place and Time of Prayer.</note> 
               <hi>That all good Chriſtian People ſhould reſt from their common Daily Buſineſs, upon the LORD's DAY, or Chriſtian Sabbath, and uſe it holily, and alſo give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to the Heavenly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of God's Holy Religion and Service.</hi> You will not wonder, if the <hi>Socinians</hi> who deny the Eternal Puniſhment of the
<note n="†" place="bottom">Volkelius <hi>de V. R lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c</hi> 15. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 29. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>And the Author of the</hi> Racovian Catechiſm, <hi>de Prophet. Chriſti munere. c.</hi> 1.</note> Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, do deny the Religious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of a Seventh Day, to be of Divine Right, and Obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry under the Goſpel. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out raiſing any Difficulties about the Morality of <hi>the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> I beſeech you, do but ſpend that Day, as believing you owe God as much Service as the Jews, or as the Ancient Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who employ'd the whole of it in Publick and Private Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:102130:80"/>as knowing what the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principles of Chriſtianity and Reaſon oblige you to, if you believe another, an Everlaſting World; and that this is all the Time you have to prepare for it; and that you have loſt a great deal; and that One Day in Seven is but a ſmall Proportion of Time. Employ that Day, as taking more Pleaſure in the Service of God, than in Earthly Buſineſs, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it the moſt honourable and delightful Work to be ſo em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd; and that accordingly you may expect the Divine Bleſſing all the Week after, and you will ſurely find it.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but take Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to juſtify, and praiſe the Attempts of <hi>the Worthy Societies for Reformation of Manners,</hi> in and about this City, one part of whoſe Buſineſs is, to ſuppreſs and puniſh ſuch a Liberty in Publick Houſes upon the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> as
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:102130:80"/>is contrary to the Commandment of God, and the Law of the Land; and tends to ruin the Souls of Men. I can eaſily believe, what I am told, That they find more Difficulty and Oppoſition in this part of their Work, than in any other, eſpecially in the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts of the City: But the Word of God, and the Teſtimony of Men's Conſciences, when awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken'd to a Sence of Sin, is on their ſide, and ſhould encourage them to proceed.</p>
            <p>I am far from reflecting upon <hi>All his Acquaintance,</hi> as if none of thoſe who were frequently in his Company, but were notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Drunkards, and Prophaners of the Sabbath: I know divers of them, of a very different Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. None but the Guilty can apprehend themſelves concern'd, in any thing he ſaid; or I ſay of him: I ſhall be heartily glad, if there be <hi>very Few,</hi> who have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:102130:81"/>to accuſe Themſelves, and that they may <hi>All</hi> profit by his Example, and Counſel.</p>
            <p>It would not be difficult, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large on the many Evils that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Drunkenneſs, and the many Sins it leads to, as diſpoſing to the violation of almoſt all the Commandments of God. I beg you would conſider the ſad Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of that Vice even in this World. How it makes Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpis'd by their Inferiours: How it impoveriſheth Families: How it occaſions Quarrels: How it wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens and deſtroys the beſt Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Health, and is often followed with manifold Diſeaſes: How it debaſes the Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; overturns our Reaſon, and ſo far deſtroys the Natural Image of God, upon the Soul; which is a greater Affront to the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of Heaven, (as one well ſays,) than if a Subject ſhould deface the King's Arms, or Image, and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:102130:81"/>ſet up the Image of a Swine, or Dog in its room. How it runs Men into Extravagancies, for which they beg Pardon the next Day; and are forgiven, with the like Shame and Contempt, as we pardon Fools, and Madmen. How it betrays the Secrets of our Heart, which Duty and Intereſt obliges to conceal; and thoſe of our deareſt Friends, which it may be, we have vow'd never to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. I beg you to conſider, how it unfits for all holy Thoughts, Words, and Actions; and is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to the <hi>being filled with the Holy Spirit:</hi> How it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſots the Mind, and hardens the Heart, ſo as to render a Man weak, and unable to make good his Reſolutions; for though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Debauch, he reſolves the next Morning, never more to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the like Folly, 'tis ten to one but he yields at the Summons of the next Temptation. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:102130:82"/>let it be conſidered, that by a Man's oppoſing his Light, and breaking his Vows and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by repeated Inſtances of Guilt in this ſort, his Conſcience muſt needs be uneaſie and clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. And hereupon he is eaſily perſwaded to ſtupify himſelf with Wine, that he may be armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Apprehenſions of his own Mind: and returns to hard Drinking, as needful for his Cure and Relief; to defend himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own Accuſing Thoughts, and try to forget his ill Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: 'Till at laſt an Habitual Sot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſs ſaves him the Labour of a daily Conflict and Skirmiſh with his Conſcience. Which is the deplorable Caſe of many who have harden'd themſelves, by Cuſtom and Continuance in Sin, ſo as to be paſt Feeling, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely ever to be brought to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. And yet the Scripture is moſt expreſs, as to the other
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:102130:82"/>World, that Men of this Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, without Repentance; <hi>ſhall never inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> 1 Cor. vi. 9, 10. Gal. v. 21. Matt. xxiv. 49, 51.</p>
            <p>I am charg'd by <hi>the Deceaſed</hi> to ſpeak at this Rate, in hope of calling Some to Repentance for their paſt Sins, and of warning Others againſt Temptation. I hope it will be conſider'd as the Faithfull Admonition of <hi>a Dying Penitent.</hi> But I have promis'd you a further Account of his <hi>Laſt Sickneſs</hi> from Another Hand, which is as follows.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:102130:83"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>An Account of ſome Paſſages of the laſt Sickneſs of Mr. S.</hi> T. <hi>by another Hand.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHEN I told him, his Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors deſpaired of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and preſs'd him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how awfull a thing it was, to appear before the Bar of a Holy God; He ſaid, he was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible it was ſo; and that it was not his leaving this World, that was his Concern; or that he fear'd the pain of Death: But what would become of his poor Soul! He, that had been ſuch a vile Wretch, and deſpis'd all the Methods, that a Gracious God had us'd to make him Happy: He had broke through all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints of Grace, the Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of a good Education, the Calls, Offers, and Warnings of God, by which he had quench'd
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:102130:83"/>and griev'd the Holy Spirit. Theſe things lay as a heavy Load upon his Soul, and broke his Reſt, and waſted his Spirits for ſome time before. He wept ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much.</p>
               <p>I asked whether <hi>Sin</hi> did not <hi>now</hi> appear an Abominable thing: And <hi>Holineſs,</hi> in the moſt Difficult parts of it, appear very Amiable: And <hi>They,</hi> the only wiſe Perſons, that ſhun, and mortify Sin, and endeavour to attain and promote Holineſs. He anſwer'd, with great Seriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Earneſtneſs, that his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, and Opinion of thoſe different courſes of Life, was ſo alterd, that he <hi>now</hi> ſaw <hi>Sin</hi> to be the only Evil, worſe than any Affliction; and that, if he knew his own Heart, which he found Deceitful, he would chuſe rather to dye, (although his Caſe was ſo hazardous,) than to live ſuch an odious Life, and diſhonour ſo
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:102130:84"/>Good a God as he had done. And he further ſaid, that he was now convinc'd, that a Holy Temper of Soul, in Conformity to God, could only make him Happy.</p>
               <p>Oh, ſaith he, my Sentiments and Notions of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> are quite otherwiſe than when in Health. What the Word of God reveals of theſe things, I feel to be Real, and Momentous indeed. Here he proceeded to charge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with Exceſs in Drinking, with Diſregard to the Sabbath Day, and a conſtant allowed Neglect of almoſt all the Poſitive Duties of Religion, eſpecially Cloſet-Retirements. And then added, <hi>Do you think there is Hope for ſuch a vile Wretch?</hi> I told him Yes, doubtleſs there was Forgiveneſs with God for the Chiefeſt of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; which I endeavour'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate from the Infiniteneſs of
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:102130:84"/>God's Mercies; the Valuableneſs of the Atonement made by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> who was,
<note place="margin">Rom. iii. 24, 28.</note> by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſet forth to be a Propitiation for our Sins, and had purchaſed our Freedom, and merited our Acceptance with his Father.</p>
               <p>I recommended the Fifth Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Chapter of the Second of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and told him he muſt ſeek Pardon and Life, in the way God had appointed; for by no other Way or Means would it be obtained. He anſwer'd, he did not hope for, nor would ſeek Salvation but by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> I told him now I hop'd his ſenſe of Sin was ſuch, as to its deſtructive and defiling Nature, as to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy him of the Juſtice of God, in entailing of the Divine Wrath upon all Mankind, as the juſt Conſequence of Original and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sins. And that the Grant of Pardon and Salvation upon the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:102130:85"/>Satisfaction and Purchaſe of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, did beſt ſuit with the Honour and Government of an Infinitely Wiſe, and Holy God, as well as with the Safety and Happineſs of us, lapſed Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>His Reply was, He was fully convinc'd, that as <hi>God</hi> was <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,</hi> ſo he was <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Holy,</hi> therefore could not Reaſonably entertain Hopes of Impunity. I told him many now-a-days pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd upon Pardon from God's General Goodneſs,
<note place="margin">Eph. i. 7.</note> as tho' his Regard to his Juſt and Holy Laws, was as mean as theirs was. He ſaid, he did not ask Pardon or Mercy, on any other Account, but <hi>for Jeſus ſake,</hi> whom God had ſet forth as a Propitiation, and through Faith in him, he was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied there was forgiveneſs for him, a Miſerable Offendor.</p>
               <p>I further told him, then I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped he was throughly convinc'd,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:102130:85"/>that our Saviour was a Divine Perſon, GOD as well as <hi>Man:</hi> This is a Myſtery above, but not contrary to Reaſon; for an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Being as God is, might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, what he was not, and yet ceaſe not to be what he was,
<note place="margin">Heb. i 3. 1 John i. 2, 3.</note> might become Man, yet ceaſe not to be God; as <hi>Phil.</hi> vi. 8. fully proves.</p>
               <p>Beſides, had Jeſus our Saviour been only a Dependent Creature, how could he have diſcharg'd our Debt by way of Satisfaction; or obtain'd for us God's Favour and Love by way of Merit? Reaſon as well as Scripture will atteſt this, to a Sinner, awaken'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of the malignity of Sin, and the pure Nature of God. Such will find no ſolid Foundation or Rational Hope, but in the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> For it was He only that was capable of honouring all thoſe Divine Attributes, Laws, and Rules of Government, that
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:102130:86"/>our Sins and Rebellions had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured and deſpiſed, by which he has render'd our Salvation both ſure and compleat,
<note place="margin">Col. i. 14, 15. Rom. iii. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> ii. 9, 10. So that God may now be juſt and holy, and yet juſtifie and ſave thoſe Penitent Sinners, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Jeſus, which if he had not been God as well as Man, He could never have effected. But now He has inhanc'd the Divine Honour and Glory, by the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Such.</p>
               <p>He reply'd, Oh! I'm abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfy'd of all this; my ſight of Sin, and the Holineſs of my Creator and Law-giver, is ſuch, that if I did not eye and own my Bleſſed Saviour, as GOD, I could not ſo account of what he did and ſuffered, as to lay the Streſs of my Salvation upon him: For <hi>as Man,</hi> he could never have ſatisfy'd Juſtice for the Breach of the Law, or merited that Mercy, or Grace I want. My applying
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:102130:86"/>what he has done, as being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by one that was <hi>God,</hi> is the Foundation of all my Truſt and Hope. And I bleſs God, who reſtrain'd me from being corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as too many are, in a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, from which now I deſire all my Support and Comfort; and he is able to ſave me to the uttermoſt. He further admir'd the Love of God in giving his Son, and of Chriſt, in giving himſelf to die, that ſuch as he might have Life. But, <hi>ſays he,</hi> I have a wretched hard Heart; it's a Stone, I can't make it Relent, or take Impreſſions from any thing I hear, or think. <hi>Oh! the Patience of God towards me, that I am out of Hell! Oh! that I could Repent!</hi> But God may juſtly leave me to my own Blindneſs and Stupidneſs, that have ſo long repulſed his Offers of Grace. <hi>Oh! horrid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude!</hi> It cuts me to the Heart. I know there is Mercy,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:102130:87"/>could I but Repent and Believe.</p>
               <p>I reply'd, That he muſt fetch <hi>Repentance,</hi> as well as <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> from Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Act. v. 31.</note> for <hi>God hath exalted him to be both a Prince and a Saviour, to give Repentance, as well as Remiſſion of Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I further told him, That Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance did produce ſuch a mighty Change upon the Soul, turning it to hate Sin, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally we love, and to eſteem, and admire, God and his Son, whom naturally we hate: That nothing but the Influences of the Almighty Spirit, could effect it. For a Sinful Nature, could not change its ſelf: Nothing can ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate above its Natural Power.</p>
               <p>I ſpent ſome time to convince him as I was able, that that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God in which we are ſaid to be Created,
<note place="margin">Rom. iii. 23. Chap v 12. Eph. iv. 24. Col. iii. 10.</note> conſiſts chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that Knowledge, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Holineſs, with which God at firſt adorn'd our Faculties,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:102130:87"/>but was ſeparable from our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and loſt by our firſt Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in <hi>Adam.</hi> And now being Children of Diſobedience, we became Children of Wrath alſo, Dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted in every Faculty, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> ii. 1, 2. till Quicken'd and Created a-new in Chriſt Jeſus, after the Divine Image, and then we ſhall be capable, and inclin'd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Sincere, Holy Obedience to God. I deſired him therefore in the Senſe of his Neceſſity, and Impotency, to addreſs himſelf ſpeedily to God, and plead the Promiſes and Merits of Jeſus, for the Gift of his Holy Spirit, to convince him throughly of Sin, and diſplay the Riches and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Free-Grace in Chriſt, and beg alſo a Correſpondent Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to God's Deſigns, and Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Goſpel, that ſo you may apply this great Salvation to your ſelf, for your Security and Bleſſedneſs.</p>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:102130:88"/>
               <p>After this Diſcourſe, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed himſelf in this manner; I find what you ſay, agreeable to my Reaſon, and that little Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge I have of Scripture. I feel, I am by Sin, an Unclean Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and as ſuch, can't cleanſe and heal my ſelf, or work Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance or Faith: They are not ſuch ſlight, eaſie things, as my ſelf once thought them to be; but poor carnal Creatures delay Repentance, as if it were in their Power to attain it, when they pleaſe: But I find by Experience <hi>now,</hi> that no leſs than the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Spirit of God, can work this Change, as you mention; and nothing leſs than ſuch a Change, is, or can be True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. I muſt hate the Sins, I naturally indulg'd, and Love, and Eſteem, and endeavour Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and Obedience to God, that by Nature and Practice I have loath'd, and deſpis'd. It is
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:102130:88"/>a Power above my own muſt work me to this. I ſee I can do nothing of my ſelf, but deſire to ſpend the little time I have, in applying my ſelf to God for Mercy and Grace.</p>
               <p>I mention'd further to him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> i. 30. Of Chriſt's being, of God, made unto us <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten, <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> to juſtifie, <hi>Sanctification</hi> to purify, and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> to free and ranſome us. And told him, in all theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, he did need, and I hop'd he would ſo accept <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He told me, he found his want in all theſe Capacities: And he was like the poor Impotent Man, that lay waiting at the Pool, for the moving of the Waters. And added, Oh! that the good Spirit of God would ſoften this hard Heart! open this blind Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding! ſubdue this ſtubborn Will! and change theſe vile Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections! and bring me to a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:102130:89"/>Cloſure with Jeſus Chriſt, as Prophet, Prieſt and King! that I may feel him to be Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification, and Redemption to me; for I am a loſt Soul without him; but I hope I do fix my Hopes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don on his Satisfaction, of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the ſight of God, on his Righteouſneſs alone, that is Spotleſs, mine is nothing but Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs at beſt. He own'd the Condeſcention and Grace of the Lord Redeemer, in executing each of thoſe Offices above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, on the Behalf, and for the Uſe of ſuch poor indigent Creatures.</p>
               <p>Sometime after, he told me he was in Danger of <hi>Preſumption</hi> at ſome times, or <hi>Deſpair</hi> at other times. That the Devil tempted him to palliate his Sins, as if he was not ſo vile, as he had made himſelf to be, and fram'd Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to leſſen his Sin, by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:102130:89"/>from Youth, Conſtitution, Temptation, Examples of Others, and the like.</p>
               <p>At other times, the Devil (ſaid he) would perſwade me, that my Confeſſion of Sin, and Sorrow, (ſuch as my own Reflections and Paſſions thereupon can produce,) is a ſufficient Repentance. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, ſaid he, in my Health, I have oft found what that could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to, when I have Sinn'd and Repented, been ſorry, and wiſh'd I had not done, or been ſo, or ſo, and reſolv'd as firmly as I could, never to doe the like, but to amend, and avoid all ſuch Evil Practices; but all this was to no purpoſe. Therefore I deſire not to truſt to my ſelf, to my own Power, but to renounce ſuch Confidence in my ſelf, as finding I am unable to change or reform my ſelf, and will doe as you hinted. I muſt go to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> to give Repentance, as well as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins.</p>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:102130:90"/>
               <p>I told him, I was rejoyc'd to hear him ſo expreſs himſelf, and bad him reſt there, and he was ſafe; for he would find <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be a Merciful and Compaſſionate <hi>Saviour.</hi> And as to his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to <hi>Preſumption</hi> and <hi>Deſpair,</hi> he muſt expect the ſtrongeſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults his Enemy could make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. True, ſaid he, but I look up to <hi>Jeſus</hi> for Succour and Reſcue.</p>
               <p>I further adviſed him to apply his Thoughts, as his Strength would permit, to conſider and weigh that Wiſe and Gracious Method laid down in the Goſpel, as before hinted, for our Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. As that the Son of God was Subſtituted in our ſtead, to make Satisfaction, and obtain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with our Offended Sovereign, by his Obedience and Sacrifice; from whence he might be furniſh'd, both with Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Strength to repell thoſe
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:102130:90"/>Temptations: For how can you have ſlight Thoughts of Sin, when you behold the Deſert of it, in the Agonies and Croſs of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Or how can you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of an Intereſt in the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges of the Covenant, which this precious Blood procured and ratified, if deſtitute of a Temper to comply with the Duties of it? It is that muſt fit you to enjoy the Bleſſings it conveys. The Summ of which is, <hi>That God will be our God:</hi> And doth it not follow, that <hi>we</hi> alſo <hi>muſt be his People?</hi> So that there can be no Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without Union to God; nor no Union, without Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance: Therefore, <hi>without Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> as <hi>none can ſee,</hi> ſo none can enjoy, or take any Pleaſure, or Complacency in <hi>God,</hi> either here or hereafter. You ſee then Tempers and Things muſt ſuit, to render us happy, by theſe Thoughts you may check <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:102130:91"/>And then againſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, Behold how God lov'd this loſt ſinful World, ſo as to give his Son to Redeem it.</hi> He made the Holy Jeſus <hi>to be Sin for us, that we might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him.</hi> 2 Cor. v. 21.</p>
               <p>He reply'd, that That Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had been of Singular Uſe to him; as alſo the Example of the <hi>Dying Penitent Thief,</hi> Luke xxiii. 42. who was embrac'd at the laſt hour. I then begg'd him to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how Remarkable <hi>his Faith</hi> was, for it was ſix'd on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> tho' hanging upon the Croſs with himſelf; yet then he cries, <hi>Lord, Remember me when thou comeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Kingdom.</hi> Now it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, none is King of Heaven, or has a Right of Donation of it, to whom he pleaſe; but he muſt be GOD, the Eternal King, that's Lord of All. So that the Thief's Truſt and Hope that he groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all upon, was the Right and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:102130:91"/>Authority <hi>Chriſt</hi> had in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kingdom, as the Matter of his Requeſt intimates.</p>
               <p>Nay further, conſider that he prayed thus, even when the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> were Crucifying this very <hi>Jeſus</hi> as a <hi>Blaſphemer,</hi> for ſaying he was <hi>the Son of God;</hi> by which he aſſerted his own Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Pray take notice from hence, how Powerful Divine Influences are upon the Mind, that could fix this Dying Malefactor upon <hi>Jeſus</hi> as <hi>GOD,</hi> thence to apply to himſelf the Validity and Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of that Salvation, that he begg'd the Grant of. And that at a time, when not only Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but Senſe alſo, ſeem'd to contradict. Oh! do you then fix <hi>your Faith,</hi> where this Bleſſed Thief did <hi>his,</hi> and diſtruſt not the <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> For <hi>Power, He is the Mighty God, the Everlaſting Father,
<note place="margin">Iſa. ix. Rom. xi. 5.</note> and the Prince of Peace.—God Bleſſed for Ever.</hi>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:102130:92"/>Again, believe him <hi>Willing,</hi> when he declares,
<note place="margin">Act. xx. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>That the weary and the heavy laden ſhall have Reſt.</hi> That Thirſty Souls may Freely drink of the Water of Life:
<note place="margin">Matth. ix. 29.</note> That he came to ſeek and to ſave the Loſt Soul; to Releaſe Captives, to bind up Broken Hearts.
<note place="margin">Iſa. lxi. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>And that whoever comes to him, he will in no wiſe caſt them off.</hi> So that you may freely and ſafely reſt your Guilty, Diſeaſed Soul upon Him; and be ſure of it, he will not Repulſe, but Embrace you, as the Father did <hi>the Prodigal Son.</hi> He reply'd, That he had found great Encouragement from that Parable, as alſo the Inſtance of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and that he found all little enough ſometimes to keep him from Deſpairing, and giving up all Hope.</p>
               <p>At another time when I went to viſit him, he again renewed his Complaints of being haunted with the ſame Temptations to
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:102130:92"/>
                  <hi>Preſumption,</hi> or <hi>Deſpair.</hi> I told him it had been of Uſe to my ſelf in the like Circumſtances, To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and reſolve Never to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any Repreſentations of the Mercy of <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> either Unworthy of the Divine Nature, or of that Conſtitution and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World, that is revealed in the Word of God, as the Rule, by which we muſt live, and God will judge: By ſuch Conſiderations, we ſhall be kept from <hi>preſuming</hi> upon Mercy and Favour, upon Lower Terms, than God has condeſcended in his Word to offer them to us: And then to prevent <hi>Deſpair,</hi> I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd, never to entertain any ſuch Thoughts of Sinfulneſs, or Impotency, as tends to diſcourage or weaken my Hopes of Mercy through Jeſus Chriſt, as held forth in the Goſpel. And ſure it is our Sinfulneſs and Emptineſs, ſhould humble, but not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:102130:93"/>drive us <hi>to,</hi> but not <hi>from</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>At the next Viſit, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd to me, of his Impotency to help himſelf, and the hardneſs and deadneſs of his Heart to any Good. I preſs'd him to get of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten read to him, the xxxvi of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek.</hi> from the 25th to the 33. <hi>ver.</hi> which I then read to him; and <hi>Jer.</hi> xxxii. 39, 40. I told him thoſe Promiſes would be of great Uſe to him, and that that Word, that God ſays <hi>I will,</hi> and <hi>you ſhall,</hi> notes the Soveraignty and Free Grace of God, and was a great Encouragement to ſuch poor Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Creatures, as he and I were, (who are not ſufficient of our ſelves to do Good,) to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to God through the Bleſſed Mediator of that Covenant, to give that <hi>Temper of Soul,</hi> that <hi>Soft Heart,</hi> there ſpoken of, together with all the other Comprehenſive Bleſſings therein promiſed.</p>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:102130:93"/>
               <p>Upon the hearing of which, he ſeem'd much refreſh'd and had them often read to him. But his weakneſs increas'd, ſo that I could not afterward diſcourſe much with him. A little before he died, he told me, he had found more Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that laſt Week in following after God, for pardoning Mercy and renewing Grace, and waiting humbly at his Foot to obtain it, than in all the ſinful or ſenſual Enjoyments of his whole Life. Nay he ſpake, as if he never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then, knew, what <hi>True Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> was: For all my Life paſt, ſaid he, is <hi>Bitterneſs</hi> to me. And let poor Sinners carry it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as ſeemingly ſatisfied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves, with their Courſe of Life: Yet they have a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Life, a ſlaviſh Life. One ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Thought, or Turn of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, damps all their Pleaſures, and fills 'em with Anguiſh; and they are forc'd to divert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:102130:94"/>with Drinking, or Gaming, or otherwiſe. And thus they are forc'd to fly from retiring into themſelves, leſt they ſhould be uneaſie. He very much lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and had a great Concern for ſome young Gentlemen, that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the ſame Courſe of Life, as he had done, and often expreſs'd an earneſt Deſire to reclaim them, by warning and admoniſhing them.</p>
               <p>To the laſt of my viſiting him, he retain'd a deep Senſe of the Evil of Sin, of his own Vileneſs, and Inſufficiency to relieve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; terming himſelf, <hi>the chiefeſt of Sinners, an ungrateful Wretch,</hi> and ſeem'd wholly to make free Grace, through Jeſus Chriſt, his Sanctuary and Refuge. He fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently mentioned the Pleaſures of a Holy Life, and his Sorrow for a ſinful one. The lv. and lxiii. Chap. of <hi>Iſa.</hi> of the Sufferings of Chriſt, was often in his Mouth,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:102130:94"/>and he ſaid, afforded him great Relief; and repeated the 7th. <hi>ver.</hi> of the lv. of <hi>Iſa.</hi> which he ſaid repreſented to him <hi>the Freeneſs, Riches,</hi> and <hi>vaſt Extent of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mercy;</hi> and indeed, had he not been clear, and fixt in that Point, he might have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettl'd in his Thoughts, as to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others.</p>
               <p>For ſome Diſcourſe, once hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd in his Chamber, upon <hi>Rom.</hi> ix. from ver. 15. to the 24. Some there ſeeming to conclude that place to hint an abſolute <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation,</hi> whatſoever we do, or endeavour. I told them, we muſt never credit ſuch a Gloſs or Senſe of a Particular Text, as ſeem'd to carry a contradiction to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and General Declaration of <hi>God</hi> in his Word. In which he often intimates, that Sinners ſhould Believe; and that he pities and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to relieve them, rather than Neceſſitates their Ruin, by ſuch a
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:102130:95"/>Decree. Tho' it's probable, that for long and uncommon Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, the Merciful God may give up ſome to ſuch a Hardneſs as the Text mentions. And that <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi>'s Caſe (as well as his Crime) ſeems to be ſingular. God's Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in the Goſpel are Univerſal, to all that will accept them, and ought not to be queſtion'd by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as if they were excluded by a peremptory Decree of Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation; becauſe <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Caſe they may think, was ſuch. 'Tis as if a Prince, upon a Univerſal Revolt of his Subjects, ſhould pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh a general Pardon, only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding ſome Traitors by Name, (ſuch as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as being more notorious than the Reſt,) and this to manifeſt his Right to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, as well as pardon: And as a Terrour to others to prevent a ſecond Revolt. Surely in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by theſe Exceptions, all the Reſt of Subjects would judge
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:102130:95"/>themſelves to be included in that general Grant, and be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged more boldly to plead it.</p>
               <p>Then it was urg'd, that <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> was not in our Power, to which Pardon is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd.</p>
               <p>I reply'd, it was true: But God had appointed Ordinances and Duties, which we muſt attend, together with earneſt, cloſe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of our Thoughts upon ſuch Truths, as have a Tendency to theſe Graces: So far it's in our Power, by common Grace and Aſſiſtance, as to the Matter of our Thoughts; and then, and not till then, may we expect, and hope the good Spirit will work them in us. Theſe are required of us, for the obtaining Faith and Repentance. So that pretend what we will, of <hi>Impoſſibilities, Difficulties,</hi> our Blood if we pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, will be upon our own Heads. Impenitency and Unbelief only will Deſtroy us.</p>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:102130:96"/>
               <p>By this Diſcourſe of <hi>Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> he ſeemed not in the leaſt diſcouraged. I told him, he was one, I hop'd, of thoſe whom Chriſt came to <hi>ſave,</hi> as ſeeing himſelf to be <hi>loſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Repeat this Diſcourſe, to ſhew Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> was ſettl'd in his Faith, that there was For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs with God through Jeſus Chriſt for <hi>him,</hi> otherwiſe this Talk of God's Decrees in his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, might have ſtaggered him.</p>
               <p>And now for a Concluſion, what Effect may be hoped for, from all that I have ſaid? You have heard from the Word of God, of the Unchangeable State of the Souls of Men, as to Happineſs or Miſery. You have ſeen the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of a good Education, and of the Knowledge of the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion betimes. You ſee the different Thoughts and Apprehenſions, that Men of any
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:102130:96"/>Parts and Senſe have of Religion, and another World, when they have leaſure to think, and are off from the Diverſions of Company, and can no longer cloud or ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle the Sentiments of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Reaſon. You have heard what amounts to a Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Serious Religion, and a Chriſtian Life; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how wiſe and adviſable it muſt be, not to run the Hazard of <hi>a late Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ſay you to theſe things? Are you concern'd in 'em or no? Are they not worth conſidering? Are there any <hi>here,</hi> ſo much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of ſecret Infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as to ſay in their Hearts, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, <q>I will run the Venture, I am not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd there will be ſuch a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Heaven, and ſuch a Terrible Hell; 'Tis true, I can't tell what will become of me after Death, but I reſolve
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:102130:97"/>to have as much as I can of the Pleaſures and Enjoyments of this Life: I hope the Fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Story of a Place of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is all or moſt of it Fancy, or Prejudice, meer Metaphor, and Parable, or Prieſtcraft, and the Bugbear of the Clergy. I hope I ſhall find it otherwiſe than Miniſters talk: I intend to run the Hazard, and to make my ſelf eaſy, I'le not read the Bible, or any other ſuch Books as may diſturb my Pleaſures, and diſquiet my Mind. And to make all ſure, I'le ſtifle and drown all my Fears by <hi>hard Drinking.</hi>
                  </q> Will you do ſo? Dare you reſolve to do ſo? Are there any ſo Beſotted, and ſo much forſaken of God? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech 'em to conſider, how little a while this Fit of Madneſs is like to laſt. And that they have no reaſon to expect, after ſo many Warnings, the extraordinary Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:102130:97"/>of God's Grace to recover 'em. For <hi>He that bleſſeth himſelf in his heart,</hi> notwithſtanding the Curſes denounc'd for Sin, <hi>ſaying, I ſhall have Peace, tho' I walk in the Imagination of my Heart, to add Drunkenneſs to Thirſt, The Lord will not ſpare him, but the Anger of the Lord, and his Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie ſhall ſmoke againſt that Man, and all the Curſes written in the Book ſhall lie upon him, and the Lord ſhall blot out his Name from under Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O, that we may all lay to Heart, theſe great and acknowledg'd Truths of our Holy Religion! And frequently and ſeriouſly conſider the Eternal Bleſſedneſs of the Saints, and the Everlaſting Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of Sinners! What a Change would it make upon all of us, if we did indeed believe 'em! How ſhould we be afraid of Sin, and of the Company and Occaſions that would intice us to Sin? and
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:102130:98" rendition="simple:additions"/>afraid of delaying our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for which there is no place after Death? How earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſpeedily ſhould we ſeek the Favour of God, and his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Mercy, and Sanctifying Grace, <hi>BY JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> the only Saviour of Sinners, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can deliver us from <hi>Wrath to come?</hi> that he may own and help us at the Hour of Death, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve us in the Day of Judgment? God grant we may all ſo Believe, and Live, as to find Mercy of the Lord, in that Day! <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:102130:98"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Printed for and Sold by</hi> John Sprint <hi>in</hi> Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-Britain.</head>
            <p>SErious Reflections on Time and Eternity, and ſome other Subjects, Moral and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; with an <hi>Appendin</hi> concerning the firſt Day of the Year, how obſerved by the Jews, and may beſt be imploy'd by a Serious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. By <hi>John Shower. Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Tradeſman's Calling;</hi> being a Diſcourſe concerning the Nature, Neceſſity, Choice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of a Calling in General, and Directions for the right managing of the Tradeſman's Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. By <hi>Richard Steel,</hi> M. A. and Miniſter of the Goſpel. 2d. Edition.</p>
            <p>Man's Sinfulneſs and Miſery by Nature. Aſſerted and Opened in ſeveral Sermons on <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians</hi> 2. <hi>Ver.</hi> 1, 2, 3. deſigned chiefly for the Unconverted. Whereunto is added, a <hi>Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> concerning the <hi>Headſhip</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Imputation</hi> of the Sin of the One, and the Righteouſneſs of the Other. By <hi>John England,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhire.</hi> 8vo.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the Old and New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Tranſlated from the French, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 200 Copper Cuts; in <hi>Quarto.</hi> Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by Dr. <hi>Hernick,</hi> and other Orthodox Divines.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of the Corruption of Scripture, Councils, and Fathers, by Prelates, Paſtors,
<pb facs="tcp:102130:99"/>and Pillars of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> Maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Popery; By <hi>Thomas James,</hi> Student in Divinity. In <hi>Octavo</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. T. Ciceronis Orationes quaedam ſelectae cum interpret. &amp; Notis in Uſum Sereniſſimi Delphini: Huic Editioni acceſſerunt Dialogi de Senectute &amp; de Amicitia 8vo.</p>
            <p>D. Junii Juvenalis &amp; A. Perſii Flacci Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae. Interpretatione ac Notis Illuſtravit Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus Bateus, Rhetoricae Profeſſor emeritus Juſſu Chriſtianiſſimi Regis in uſum ſereniſſimi Delphini. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Works of Mr. <hi>John Cleveland,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his Poems, Orations, and Epiſtles: Alſo the Ruſtick Rampant, or Rural Anarchy affronting Monarchy, in the Inſurrection of <hi>Wat. Tyler;</hi> Collected into one Volume, with the Life of the Author. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Illiads and Odyſſes of <hi>Homer,</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of Greek into Engliſh; By <hi>Thomas Hebbes</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury.</hi> Alſo the Life of <hi>Homer.</hi> The Third Edition. In <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fidelis Achates:</hi> Or an Hiſtorical Account of the moſt Remarkable Actions in the late Reigns, and the Preſent Revolution, in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roiok Verſe. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102130:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
